<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practice of thankefulnesse; or Davids choyse directions how to prayse God In an exposition and application vpon the whole sixtie sixe Psalme. With a short treatise vpon the thirtie one, and thirtie two verses of the one hundred and seuenth psalme.</title>
            <author>[Larke, Nicholas]</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15254.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124556</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1967:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practice of thankefulnesse; or Davids choyse directions how to prayse God In an exposition and application vpon the whole sixtie sixe Psalme. With a short treatise vpon the thirtie one, and thirtie two verses of the one hundred and seuenth psalme.</title>
                  <author>[Larke, Nicholas]</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by G. P[urslowe]. for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shop, neere to the Conduit in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1: An exposition of the sixtie sixe Psalme, by doctrine and examination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXVI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXI-XXXII --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional exercises --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRACTICE OF Thankefulneſſe; OR DAVIDS choyſe directions how to prayſe GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In an Expoſition and Application vpon</hi> the whole ſixtie ſixe PSALME.</p>
            <p>With a ſhort Treatiſe vpon the thirtie one, and thirtie two Verſes of the one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſeuenth PSALME.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. THESS. 5.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
In all things giue thankes, for this is the will of God, in Chriſt Ieſus towards you.</q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, neere to the Conduit in Fleet-ſtreet. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150664:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150664:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE, VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVOVS, AND CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN LADIE, THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Counteſſe of <hi>Lincolne:</hi> Lady-Mother to the Illuſtrious, and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religious Earle of <hi>Lincolne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt worthy Ladie, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent it is, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercie hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched you with that,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.</note> which is more precious then the beſt tried gold; with that Faith,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</note> which is attended on with the luſtre of Vertue, the grace of Knowledge, the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of Temperance, the ornament of a meeke and quiet Spirit, the ſupport of Patience, the ſplendour of Humilitie, the gaine of Godlineſſe, the bond of Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb facs="tcp:150664:3"/>kindneſſe, and the glorie of Loue. And albeit the moſt righteous Lord hath darkened your comfort in the weakeſt, yet hath hee most brightly lighted it with a manifold ſhine in the greatest: Here there ſhineth remembrance of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in youth; in youth, learning to know Time, and Reaſon; diſcretion to anſwer the enemies in the gate; wiſedome to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre and chuſe that, whoſe price is farre aboue the Rubies; ſatisfaction to your Honor, and hope of wiſhed glorie to your moſt Noble houſe, and generous race. O, the lines are falne to your Honour in moſt pleaſant places, ſo that you are able to ſay to the profane wonderers, and to all your Peeres, Maruell not that I am zealous of reading, hearing, and meditation; maruell not that I loue not this world, nor the euils thereof, the luſts of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life; maruell not that I ſtudie to haue my conuerſation
<pb facs="tcp:150664:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>in heauen; or that I call ſo often for the exerciſes of Prayer, Preaching, and Thankeſgiuing; for God hath done ſo great things for my ſoule, as I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be thankefull enough.</p>
            <p>O moſt Christian Counteſſe; two things I haue often thought vpon: the one, how I might ſatisfie the continuall requeſt of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Chriſtian friends, by ſome fruits of my vnpoliſhed labours: the other, how I might teſtifie to the world, my moſt reſpectiue du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to your Honour: now at length for the ſatisfaction of the one, and teſtification of the other, I haue preſumed to tender that, which alwayes hitherto I trembled to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, becauſe of my weaknes; fearing the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of ſome <hi>Momus,</hi> for bringing no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty amidſt ſo much variety: or ſome <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſhould blame me, for bringing any more amidſt ſo much ſacietie. Yet conſidering, that ſince the time of Reformation is come, the Temple of the Lord is in more places
<pb facs="tcp:150664:4"/>then <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and of ſuch ſpacious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, as though knowledge abound there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as the Sea; yet there is place ſtill emptie to receiue it. And now the Builders are not ſo many, and the fit ſtuffe is not ſo much, but that there is a renewed charge, that towards the Lords Worke euerie one bring what hee can, that as hee hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the gift, hee ſhould minister the ſame to other, as good Stewards of the manifold graces and gifts of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſome little of that ſpirituall bleſsing, which his holy Spirit hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to mee, his vnworthy inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in meditation, according to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie laid vpon mee, I haue vttered, and ministred to others in preaching, and here doe preſent, as to all my fellow-members, and Chriſtian friends euery where: but firſt, and chiefly to your moſt Honourable and vertuous ſelfe, in writing. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and ground of my labour, is the ſixtie
<pb facs="tcp:150664:4"/>ſixe Pſalme, a Pſalme of Diuine praiſe, made by the ſweet Pſalmiſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the deliuerance of Gods people out of many ſore calamities, and of himſelfe out of the bloudie hands of his perſecuting e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. I wiſh it to all, becauſe all haue more then much need to bee awaked, to this dutie of praiſing God in this time of ſecuritie: but I dedicate it onely to your Honour, as to the prime moouer of this my preſent indeuour.</p>
            <p>For, when I had neither a purpoſe to any ſuch Treatiſe, nor thought of this moſt worthy Pſalme: then did your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whoſe affections are euer ſet on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, name this Song and Pſalme vnto mee, commend it to my meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, requeſt mee to intreat of it, helpe my labours with your prayers, and ioyfully heard what the Lord ſpake by mee out of it. Therefore, I beſeech your Honour, take this my Dedication, as a true token
<pb facs="tcp:150664:5"/>of my moſt gratefull affection to your moſt Noble ſelfe, another <hi>Marie</hi> in chuſing the better part: as a teſtimony of my longing to adde ſomething to the cure of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable neglect of holy duties: and as a witneſſe of my deſire to further this ſeruice, to Gods praiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and glorie. Euen ſo bee it, euen ſo bee it, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours euer to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Lord, N. LARKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150664:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION OF the ſixtie ſixe PSALME, by Doctrine and <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this <hi>holy Pſalme,</hi> conſider:
<note place="margin">The Title.</note> Firſt, the <hi>Title:</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Pſalme</hi> it ſelfe: the Title com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it, <hi>To the chiefe Muſician,</hi> or the <hi>Maſter of the harmony,</hi> or <hi>Him that excelleth;</hi> and intitles it, <hi>A Song, A Pſalme,</hi> as being one of that kind, which the Church in <hi>Dauids</hi> time v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſing with Inſtruments &amp; voyces. It ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>well</hi> to prepare attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and intention to the matter of the Pſalme. For it may plainly teach vs: Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That it is worthy of chiefe <hi>skill,</hi> and conſent in ſinging the ſame:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That it is a Song full of <hi>Excellencie,</hi> and to bee vſed ſo, as our Diuine praiſes may be made more pleaſing, <hi>ſweet,</hi> and excellent by it. Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That it is to bee ſung with a double <hi>Muſicke,</hi> and melodie to <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19.</note> euen
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150664:6"/>with the glorie of the Tongue,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> and the grace of the <hi>Heart:</hi> loe, how the Title is a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue to the vnderſtanding, affecting, and vſing of this ſpeciall <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which there is:
<note place="margin">The Pſalme</note> Firſt, A generall; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, A particular ſetting foorth of the praiſe of <hi>God:</hi> by diligent peruſing whereof, wee ſhall learne much worthy and neceſſarie knowledge: knowledge, how to make <hi>Gods</hi> praiſe <hi>glorious:</hi> to comfort our ſelues in his greatneſſe: to reioyce in his noble <hi>Workes:</hi> to ſucke ſweetneſſe out of our <hi>afflictions:</hi> and to relate without either affectation, or oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to God <hi>glorie,</hi> and to others edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Lords</hi> admirable <hi>goodneſſe</hi> vnto eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of vs, and to awake vs vnto all theſe; thus this <hi>Pſalme</hi> beginneth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Make a ioyfull noiſe vnto God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1.</note> all yee lands.</hi>] In giuing <hi>God</hi> thankes, it is our dutie to haue great reioycing; they that doe it without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, yea, euen in him, doe it not ſo right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as is fitting to his <hi>Maieſtie.</hi> Therefore in doing this dutie, reioyce greatly, be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to let thy reioycing be ſeene, and heard; make a ioyfull <hi>noyſe,</hi> like the noyſe of the Trumpets in the <hi>dayes</hi> of your <hi>triumphs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 10.9.10.</note> of your gladneſſe, of your feſtiuall <hi>ſolemnities,</hi> and of the times wherein you found ſpeciall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150664:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>acceptation of your <hi>ſacrifices:</hi> and make this noyſe vnto God.</p>
            <p>Diuine thankeſgiuing, is to bee appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate onely to <hi>Gods perſon.</hi> Deny it to all creatures in heauen, or earth: deny it to falſe gods,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 68.19.</note> and giue it to the true euerliuing <hi>God,</hi> the God of our <hi>ſaluation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">90.17.</note> our owne <hi>God,</hi> euen the <hi>God</hi> that ſaueth vs, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth his <hi>grace</hi> in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All yee lands.</hi>] None of the vniuerſall <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is exempt from prayſing <hi>God:</hi> high, low, <hi>Iew, Gentile, bond, free, male, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> hold not backe your praiſe from <hi>God;</hi> hee holds not backe his <hi>benefits</hi> from you,
<note place="margin">65.19.</note> but ladeth you daily with the ſame: you haue,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note> or can haue nothing, but what you receiue from him, and that, not for your merit, but onely for his <hi>mercie,</hi> which indureth for <hi>euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sing forth the honour of his Name,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 2.</note> make his praiſe glorious.</hi>] True <hi>Thankeſgiuing</hi> is ſuch an action, as cheerefully ſets forth the <hi>glorie</hi> of <hi>Gods Name:</hi> let not your thankes to <hi>God,</hi> the moſt High ouer all in <hi>heauen,</hi> and <hi>earth,</hi> bee any abaſing of his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> but aſcribe that to his great and fearefull <hi>Name,</hi> which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 29.2, 8.</note> giue to him the <hi>glorie</hi> due to his <hi>Name,</hi> let euery one that ſpeakes of him, ſpeake of his <hi>glory:</hi> confeſſe that his Name is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150664:7"/>aboue euery name in <hi>heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10</note> and <hi>earth:</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that at his <hi>Name</hi> euery knee ſhould bow, of things in heauen, and in earth, and things vnder the earth.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.10.</note> Confeſſe that his Name is a ſtrong Tower to all that truſt in him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that his <hi>Name</hi> is <hi>wonderfull</hi> excellent in all the <hi>world:</hi> confeſſe that his glorious <hi>Name</hi> is greater then all thankeſgiuing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.5.</note> and praiſe: let the deſires of your ſoule be to the praiſe of his holy Name.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Make his praiſe glorious.</hi>] Diuine <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> makes <hi>Gods</hi> praiſe <hi>glorious;</hi> glorious to the hearing, and vnderſtanding of men, though it can ſupply no defect of <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> for his <hi>glory</hi> is alwayes <hi>infinite,</hi> and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute: leſſen not his <hi>praiſe,</hi> praiſe him not <hi>baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> giue not his <hi>praiſe</hi> to any other: ſo praiſe him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 108.1, 2</note> as becommeth <hi>him:</hi> let your hearts bee prepared, and your tongues awaked, to vtter forth the greateſt praiſe you can of Gods Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say yee:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3.</note>] Thankeſgiuing</hi> is to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſpeaking: bee not ſilent from this <hi>dutie;</hi> auoyd that ſilence, as great diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: neither can you excuſe it by pleading ignorance: here you are <hi>taught</hi> what to ſay. Hee that requireth your <hi>thankſgiuing,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you what you ſhould <hi>ſpeake</hi> in the ſame:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150664:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>hee that commandeth to make his <hi>praiſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> ſheweth, how you ſhould make it glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: of his goodneſſe hee findeth you heart, mouth, tongue, words, and all; that to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this dutie, you ſhould haue no excuſe at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say yee vnto God:</hi>] In <hi>praiſing God,</hi> that muſt onely be ſaid of him, which may with a good <hi>conſcience</hi> be ſaid euen to him. Vſe not the <hi>Lord</hi> as you doe men, to ſay one thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind his <hi>backe,</hi> and another afore his <hi>face:</hi> for you can neuer bee but in his ſight, neuer thinke a thought, but hee vnderſtands <hi>it;</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake a word, but hee knowes <hi>it:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay yee things <hi>glorious</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> and ſay ye the ſame vnto him. Shew that his <hi>benefits,</hi> his <hi>Name,</hi> his <hi>glory,</hi> and his <hi>praiſe</hi> doe ſo affect you, as you cannot, but like a gratefull man to a moſt beneficiall friend, meet the <hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God</hi> in your <hi>meditations,</hi> and breaking out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to zealous <hi>praiſes</hi> of his bountie, ſpeake, and ſay euen vnto <hi>himſelfe,</hi> that which may beſt teſtifie, how deſirous you are to ſhew your beſt <hi>thankefulneſse</hi> for all his louing kindneſſe: hence ſay yee vnto <hi>God:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How terrible,</hi> or <hi>reuerend art thou in thy workes!</hi>] To the high ſetting forth of <hi>Gods praiſe,</hi> is required a feeling <hi>confeſsion</hi> of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150664:8"/>moſt reuerend dealing in euery <hi>action.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware you want not the conſideration, that ſhould bring this <hi>confeſsion;</hi> they are neere deſtruction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 28.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.12.</note> and the ſound of great woe is to them, that regard not the <hi>worke</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and conſider not the operation of his <hi>hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.43.</note> Doe you otherwiſe, bee you wiſe to <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> the wayes of <hi>God,</hi> be you carefull to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thoſe things in <hi>Gods adminiſtration,</hi> which may teach you this feeling <hi>confeſsion,</hi> that you may ſay vnto him with <hi>admiration;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 8.1.</note> How excellent, <hi>O Lord,</hi> is thy <hi>Name</hi> in all the earth?
<note place="margin">92.7.</note> How great and <hi>glorious</hi> are thy <hi>workes?</hi> And how innumerable is the number of them?
<note place="margin">104.24.</note> How <hi>vnſearchable</hi> are thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 15.11.</note> Who is like to thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> among the gods? So glorious in <hi>holineſſe,</hi> fearefull in <hi>prayſes,</hi> and doing <hi>wonders.</hi> Thou ſo ruleſt in the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> aboue,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.32.</note> and ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt in the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the earth below, as to thee wee alwayes <hi>ſay, How reuerend and fearefull art thou in thy workes?</hi> the like where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of none can doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Through the greatneſſe of thy power.</hi>] It is a principall point in the praiſing of <hi>God,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the <hi>glory</hi> of victory to his <hi>power</hi> onely; ſay not, Our own arme ſhall <hi>ſaue vs;</hi> our <hi>Idols</hi> haue ſaued vs; our <hi>Horſes,</hi> and <hi>Chariots</hi> ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150664:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaue vs: but euer ſay vnto <hi>God</hi> in euery <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Thou, O <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 76.4.</note> art more <hi>glorious</hi> and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, then the higheſt helpes;
<note place="margin">115.1.</note> onely at thy <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke</hi> both the <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Chariot</hi> are caſt <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe;</hi> Not vnto vs, O <hi>Lord,</hi> not vnto vs, but to thy <hi>Name</hi> we giue the <hi>glory. Thou, euen thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, by the greatneſſe of thy power, hast gotten thy ſelfe the victory;</hi> and <hi>through this power</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall thine enemies ſubmit themſelues vnto thee, though diſſemblingly.</hi>] When wee ſee Gods enemies driuen for feare to diſſemble <hi>Religion,</hi> and not to dare to withſtand the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendours,</hi> and Miniſters of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdome, wee ſhould admire, and acknowledge <hi>Gods</hi> mighty power therin: ſay not, This is through <hi>mans policie:</hi> ſay not, This is for feare of mans <hi>power:</hi> but <hi>confeſse</hi> and ſay, Behold the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>power</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 6.</note> Heatheniſh <hi>Darius</hi> ſubmitted himſelfe vnto thee, and forwarded the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thy <hi>Temple:</hi> through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan. q.</hi> 37.</note> great <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe vnto thee, and <hi>extolled,</hi> and <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and <hi>honoured</hi> thee, the King of <hi>Heauen:</hi> through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power,</hi> hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſubmitted himſelfe to thee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 12.31.</note> to let thine <hi>Iſrael</hi> goe. So ſtill ſhall thine enemies, and the enemies of thy <hi>Christ,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150664:9"/>themſelues vnto thy <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thine enemies.</hi>] All are not true friends to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that vnder Chriſtian <hi>Kings,</hi> and in the <hi>Churches</hi> proſperitie profeſſe the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power,</hi> O <hi>God,</hi> ſome are thy enemies, and therefore not to be truſted by thy <hi>ſeruants</hi> (becauſe they, in reſpect of the betterneſſe of the times, and ſome other hand of thine, dare doe no other:) Some are in ſubiection vnto thee, and ſubmit themſelues among thy people, as <hi>Iudas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thine <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> onely they doe it ſore againſt their <hi>heart;</hi> they doe it with deſire ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of opportunitie to caſt off thy <hi>yoke,</hi> and to ſhew their enmitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſſemblingly, and lyingly.</hi>] They come neere <hi>Gods</hi> enemies, that ſerue him in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, or for ſeruile feare of his <hi>power,</hi> and not in <hi>truth</hi> and ſinceritie, for <hi>dutie,</hi> and loue to his <hi>Maieſtie.</hi> Looke to your <hi>hearts,</hi> that you haue not guiltie <hi>conſciences</hi> this way, ſo as you may wofully accuſe your ſelues, ſaying, Through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power,</hi> we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues vnto thee, and to thy <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> onely in diſſimulation, and perforce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we dare doe none other:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 125.4.</note> but be yee ſo good,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</note> and true of heart, as you may find your ſelues in a child-like <hi>ſubmiſsion,</hi> with <hi>faith</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150664:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>and pure loue; and ſo may ſay this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>God,</hi> onely of his enemies, <hi>Through the greatneſſe of thy power, thine enemies fainedly ſubmit themſelues vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the earth ſhall worſhip thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note>] There is no reſpect of perſon, in <hi>Gods</hi> Vocation of men to <hi>ſaluation.</hi> Be not diſcouraged, becauſe thou art a <hi>Gentile,</hi> or <hi>bond,</hi> or <hi>female,</hi> or <hi>weake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34, 35.</note> or a thing of nothing: <hi>God</hi> calls all that are his, the <hi>Gentile,</hi> aſſoone as the <hi>Iew,</hi> the <hi>bond,</hi> aſſoone as the <hi>free,</hi> the <hi>female,</hi> aſſoone as the <hi>male,</hi> the <hi>weake,</hi> aſſoone as the <hi>ſtrong:</hi> he puts no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, hee doth nothing for any ones <hi>perſon</hi> ſake, but all <hi>for</hi> his owne <hi>mercy</hi> ſake. Hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not his <hi>Church</hi> within ſome one <hi>Town, Citie, Nation,</hi> or <hi>Countrey,</hi> but many come from all <hi>Regions,</hi> to ſit downe with <hi>Abraham,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.11.</note> Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iaakob,</hi> in his <hi>kingdome;</hi> and all this through his power: through the greatneſſe of thy power, <hi>All the earth ſhall worſhip thee.</hi>] It is Gods praiſe onely, that his people doe <hi>worſhip</hi> him. If you be worſhippers of God, praiſe not your owne <hi>wel-willing</hi> that way, your owne ſelfe-affection to <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> your owne apprehenſion of the meanes, the power of the inſtruments: but praiſe the riches of Gods <hi>grace,</hi> and the power of his <hi>Spirit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6, 8, 10.</note> and ſay vnto him, Of our <hi>ſelues</hi> wee are weake, we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150664:10"/>are <hi>ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.32.</note> wee are <hi>enemies,</hi> wee are <hi>vngodly.</hi> Now that we are turned to <hi>worſhip</hi> thee, thine is the <hi>praiſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.44.</note> thou haſt called vs vnto it, thou haſt <hi>drawne</hi> vs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 65.4.</note> thou haſt <hi>cauſed</hi> vs to come vnto thee, onely through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power</hi> we <hi>worſhip</hi> thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all ſhall ſing vnto thee.</hi>] Singing rightly, is a ſinging vnto God <hi>himſelfe.</hi> Sing not holy <hi>Hymnes,</hi> ſpirituall <hi>Songs,</hi> diuine <hi>Pſalmes</hi> to your owne mindes carnally merry, or to pleaſe the vncircumciſed <hi>eares</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane <hi>friends:</hi> but ſing them ſo, as you doe certainely <hi>ſing</hi> them vnto God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> making a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody in your <hi>heart</hi> vnto him, and ſinging them to him with <hi>grace</hi> in your <hi>mindes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sing vnto thee.</hi>] Right ſinging vnto GOD, is a part of the <hi>worſhip</hi> of God: an effect of the gracious <hi>operation</hi> of GOD: an action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to euery member of the <hi>Church</hi> of GOD. All the earth ſhall, in <hi>worſhipping</hi> thee, ſing vnto thee; through thy <hi>power</hi> they ſhall ſing vnto thee, and all they ſhall <hi>ſing</hi> vnto thee. If you neuer ſing vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> how doe you giue him his whole <hi>worſhip?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.4, 32.</note> Where is his ioyfull <hi>Seruice?</hi> Therefore as you ſay vnto him, ſo <hi>ſing</hi> vnto him, ſing <hi>daily</hi> vnto him, ſing <hi>praiſes,</hi> ſing praiſes, ſing skilfull prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150664:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>They ſhall ſing to thy Name excellently.</hi>] The chiefeſt, and <hi>worthieſt</hi> renowme that can bee ſpoken of <hi>people,</hi> is, that they be <hi>religious,</hi> and zealous <hi>worſhippers</hi> of GOD. In aſcribing vnto God the <hi>glory</hi> due vnto him, ſay this chiefly vnto him, Hee rein is thy praiſe <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> that through the greatneſſe of thy <hi>power,</hi> people doe <hi>worſhip</hi> thee, and ſing vnto thy <hi>Name</hi> excellently: this being GODS ſpeciall <hi>honour</hi> to effect this, it is our ſpeciall <hi>renowne,</hi> that it is <hi>effected</hi> in vs: if any bee not a true <hi>worſhipper</hi> of GOD, hee hath no renowne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 49.20.</note> he is without <hi>honour,</hi> hee is moſt <hi>baſe,</hi> hee is euen <hi>abominable.</hi> But they that are made his <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers,</hi> are <hi>noble</hi> in <hi>name,</hi> in <hi>praiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.19</note> and in <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> aboue all other: and this is the <hi>glory</hi> of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Kings,</hi> to bring <hi>preſents</hi> to him, to offer <hi>gifts</hi> to him, to fall downe to <hi>worſhip</hi> him, and to <hi>ſerue</hi> him. Therefore, thinke your ſelues greatly <hi>exalted,</hi> that you are become his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>ſeruants, reioyce</hi> in this againſt all <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> abaſements, and hope after the increaſe of the number of his true <hi>worſhippers,</hi> and ſay ſtill vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> with confident expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>reſtoring</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and of the fulfilling of the <hi>Gentiles,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> All the earth ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thee, they ſhall ſing to thee, they ſhall ſing to thy Name excellently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150664:11"/>
               <hi>Come,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 5.</note> and ſee the workes of God.</hi>] Vnto the <hi>worſhipping</hi> of GOD rightly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.31.</note> is required a willing comming to the <hi>meanes</hi> that teach vs his <hi>glory:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.2. <hi>Iob</hi> 21.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18</note> ſay not as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> It is <hi>hereſie</hi> to come: or with the <hi>rebellious</hi> and voluptuous, Wee will not come: or with the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> What profit is it to come?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.5.</note> or with <hi>worldlings,</hi> Wee cannot come:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1.</note> or with <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> Wee are too <hi>holy</hi> to come:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28</note> but with the <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry</hi> and thirſtie come; with them that are bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened and <hi>heauy laden</hi> come,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 2.3.</note> with them that are <hi>zealous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.45.</note> prouoke one another to come, with them that are <hi>taught</hi> of GOD come;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 34.11.</note> and you ſhall not come in <hi>vaine,</hi> but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the <hi>meanes,</hi> you ſhall learne the <hi>feare</hi> of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come.</hi>] The Miniſtery of the <hi>Word</hi> of God teacheth, and inuiteth vs to make vſe, and godly benefit of the <hi>workes</hi> of GOD, that bids vs <hi>come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 95. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.17.</note> and let vs not be abſent, not from <hi>this; neglect</hi> not this; <hi>harden</hi> not your <hi>hearts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this; but <hi>frequent</hi> this, <hi>heare</hi> this, <hi>beleeue</hi> this, <hi>obey</hi> this, <hi>ſubmit</hi> your <hi>ſelues</hi> to this &amp; <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> how you <hi>profit</hi> by this; and according to the preſent <hi>charge</hi> of this, <hi>Come and ſee.</hi>] The way to the profitable vſe of the <hi>meanes</hi> of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 42.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.13.</note> is to ſee, <hi>behold,</hi> and conſider the ſame. Come not as <hi>hypocrites</hi> to diſſemble: come
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150664:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>not as <hi>ſluggards,</hi> to ſleepe:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez.</hi> 33.32.</note> come not as <hi>ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> to deride, nor as <hi>enemies,</hi> to catch, nor as <hi>children</hi> and fooles, to gaze, prattle, or <hi>play;</hi> but come as the <hi>louers</hi> of <hi>goodnes,</hi> to <hi>ſeek;</hi> as the <hi>wiſe,</hi> to <hi>obſerue;</hi> come as the <hi>godly,</hi> to <hi>learne,</hi> as the <hi>prudent,</hi> to conſider, and as the <hi>obedient,</hi> to ſee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Workes of the Lord.</hi>] The <hi>workes</hi> of GOD are ſpeciall meanes to furniſh vs, and fit vs to <hi>worſhip</hi> and praiſe GOD. Doe not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme them as dead things; doe not paſſe by them as idle <hi>matters,</hi> &amp; of no reckoning; doe not <hi>ſinne,</hi> as thoſe that are complained of, for that they regarded not the <hi>workes</hi> of GOD, nor conſidered the <hi>operation</hi> of his <hi>hands;</hi> but come, and <hi>behold</hi> his <hi>workes,</hi> vſe them as happy <hi>meanes</hi> to make thee happy, that is, to fit thee to bee an happy and holy <hi>worſhipper</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>Vſe his <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>creation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. 9. 36. 6. 31. 23. 7, 8, 9, 10. 67. 4. 9. 16. 145. 15, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 111. 9.</note> to draw you to <hi>feare</hi> him; his <hi>workes</hi> of common <hi>preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to admire his <hi>prouidence;</hi> his <hi>workes</hi> of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>preſeruation,</hi> to <hi>loue</hi> him; of <hi>adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to truſt and to <hi>reioyce</hi> in him; of <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to <hi>acknowledge</hi> him, and to ſtand in awe of him; of <hi>ſuſtentation</hi> to <hi>waite</hi> on him: and his <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>redemption,</hi> to <hi>praiſe</hi> his <hi>holy</hi> and fearefull <hi>Name:</hi> in ſtead of vaine and corrupt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150664:12"/>communication,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.2, 5</note> talke of his <hi>wonderfull works,</hi> and in ſtead of remembring vanities, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his maruellous <hi>workes</hi> which hee hath done, his <hi>wonders,</hi> and the <hi>iudgements</hi> of his <hi>mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee is to be reuerenced in his doing toward the ſonnes of men.</hi>] They that rightly conſider Gods working, doe find that hee is moſt <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to bee <hi>reuerenced</hi> in euery <hi>action:</hi> O thou man, that doeſt not perceiue this, thou art very <hi>fooliſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.</note> But yee <hi>holy</hi> ones, whom God hath made <hi>glad</hi> through his <hi>workes,</hi> and who reioyce in the <hi>worke</hi> of his <hi>hands;</hi> happy are you, for you ſee how true this is, and you <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> that hee is ſo reuerend in his <hi>doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Toward the ſonnes of men.</hi>] The very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, toward whom God is ſo reuerend in his dealing, is full of argument of his <hi>commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> for who bee theſe? Euen the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men. Oh then, <hi>praiſe</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> highly for his <hi>adminiſtration</hi> to ſuch perſons: confeſſe his <hi>bountie</hi> vnto theſe, bountie <hi>vnſpeakable;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his <hi>goodneſse</hi> vnto theſe, goodneſſe <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable;</hi> confeſſe his <hi>mercy</hi> to theſe, <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> moſt laudable; confeſſe his <hi>loue</hi> to theſe, loue moſt <hi>admirable.</hi> For theſe haue plunged themſelues into all <hi>miſery:</hi> theſe haue prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his <hi>wrath</hi> by infinite <hi>iniquity:</hi> theſe haue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150664:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>nothing in them to deſerue any <hi>compaſsion:</hi> theſe haue all that is in them to bring <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> O wee men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.</note> whoſe <hi>imaginations</hi> are continually <hi>euill,</hi> whoſe fooliſh <hi>mindes</hi> are full of <hi>darknes,</hi> whoſe very <hi>hearts</hi> are moſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull,</hi> whoſe <hi>mouthes</hi> are full of <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> whoſe <hi>throates</hi> are an open <hi>ſepulcher,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</note> whoſe <hi>eyes</hi> are full of <hi>vanity,</hi> whoſe <hi>eares</hi> are full of <hi>idleneſſe,</hi> whoſe <hi>hands</hi> are full of <hi>bloud,</hi> whoſe <hi>feet</hi> are ſwift to euery <hi>miſchiefe,</hi> whoſe <hi>life</hi> is moſt <hi>ſinfull,</hi> and whoſe <hi>body</hi> is moſt <hi>vile:</hi> Let vs <hi>wonder</hi> that <hi>God</hi> is ſo reuerend in his <hi>dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to ſuch moſt vnworthy <hi>perſons,</hi> and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, let vs to his <hi>glory</hi> ſay, What is <hi>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</note> that thou art ſo fauourable a <hi>God</hi> vnto him? What is wretched <hi>man,</hi> that thou art <hi>mindfull</hi> of him? What is the <hi>ſonne</hi> of mortall <hi>man,</hi> that thou viſiteſt him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee turned the ſea into dry land.</hi>]
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 6.</note> God ſhewes himſelfe <hi>wonderfull</hi> in his doing, for them that feare him: Their <hi>enemies</hi> were <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde</hi> them, the <hi>Red Sea</hi> is before them: What now ſhall become of them? Why,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.9.</note> 
               <hi>behold</hi> the <hi>ſaluation</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> to his owne <hi>people,</hi> hee forthwith <hi>rebuked</hi> the deepe <hi>Sea</hi> for ſtaying them, and it preſently gaue <hi>way</hi> vnto them, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelming all their <hi>enemies</hi> that followed them. See how reuerend the <hi>Lord</hi> was in his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150664:13"/>doing toward theſe <hi>ſonnes</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> ioyne your ſelues to this <hi>God,</hi> and hee will doe <hi>wonders</hi> for you; <hi>beleeue</hi> in him, and hee will make all things <hi>poſsible</hi> vnto you; expect with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence his <hi>deliuerance,</hi> if no <hi>meanes</hi> bee with you; if all <hi>meanes</hi> bee againſt you, yet can hee find <hi>meanes</hi> to helpe, and <hi>ſaue</hi> you; he turned the <hi>ſea</hi> into dry <hi>land:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They went thorow the flood on foot.</hi>] To whom <hi>God</hi> makes himſelfe knowne in a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>fauour,</hi> and manner, to them hee will <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie</hi> his <hi>power:</hi> that they might ſee his great <hi>ſaluation,</hi> hee led them dry <hi>ſhod</hi>-thorow the great <hi>depths</hi> of the cruell <hi>ſea:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3.10.</note> and after, that they might <hi>know</hi> that hee the liuing <hi>Lord</hi> was among them, and that hee would not <hi>faile</hi> to doe all that hee <hi>promiſed</hi> them, hee cut off the <hi>waters</hi> of the Riuer <hi>Iordan,</hi> and made them ſtand on an <hi>heape,</hi> euen when it was at the broadeſt, vntill all his <hi>ſeruants</hi> were cleane gone. If hee doe not thus to you, but lets <hi>ſeas</hi> and flouds of <hi>iniquitie</hi> keepe you from <hi>entring</hi> into his <hi>holy Canaan,</hi> then <hi>lament;</hi> for it argues that he yet hath no <hi>ſauour</hi> vnto you: if you would haue him thus <hi>magnifie</hi> his <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> ſome <hi>way</hi> towards you, then <hi>call</hi> your <hi>ſelues</hi> by the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Iaakob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.5.</note> and ſubſcribe with your <hi>hand</hi> vnto the <hi>Lord:</hi> if you bee his <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150664:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>then expect one great <hi>deliuerance</hi> after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: and if you <hi>know</hi> who <hi>feare</hi> him, doe not <hi>mocke</hi> nor <hi>deſpiſe</hi> them; but ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 33.29</note> They are <hi>happy;</hi> ſay, Who is like vnto them, ſo <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> by the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>ſhield</hi> of their <hi>helpe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There did we reioyce in him.</hi>] Gods <hi>admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and comfortable <hi>dealing</hi> begets preſent <hi>reioycing</hi> in him, in them that <hi>loue</hi> and feare him. They were no ſooner paſſed thorow the <hi>Red Sea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.</note> but then and there <hi>Moſes</hi> and the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſang <hi>ioyfully,</hi> a ſong of <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> vnto the <hi>Lord:</hi> there alſo <hi>Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> the Propheteſſe, with all the <hi>women</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>men,</hi> with well-tuned <hi>inſtruments, holy</hi> dances, and ſweet <hi>voyces</hi> in the ſame <hi>thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing:</hi> There did they <hi>reioyce</hi> in nothing of their owne, in nothing of any <hi>creature</hi> in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> or <hi>earth,</hi> in nothing <hi>elſe</hi> but in <hi>God</hi> alone, in his <hi>triumph</hi> alone, in his <hi>ſtrength</hi> alone, in his <hi>ſaluation</hi> alone, in his <hi>Name</hi> alone, in his right <hi>hand</hi> alone, in his <hi>power</hi> alone, and in his <hi>greatnes</hi> alone. But doe wee not <hi>honour</hi> him in the very <hi>place</hi> where hee hath <hi>honoured</hi> vs? Not <hi>praiſe</hi> him in the very time, wherein hee hath done <hi>great</hi> things for vs? Not <hi>reioyce</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt all our comforts, <hi>benefits,</hi> and <hi>deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances?</hi> Are wee not now moſt <hi>glad,</hi> that hee giues vs bleſſed proofs, that he is become our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150664:14"/>
               <hi>owne God,</hi> ſtrength, <hi>deliuerer,</hi> and <hi>ſaluation?</hi> Oh let vs <hi>tremble</hi> at this <hi>vnthankfulneſſe,</hi> and ſo <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend</hi> this negligence, as we may ſay <hi>iustly,</hi> as they haue ſaid, <hi>There, there did wee reioyce in him:</hi> and ſtill may wee reioyce in him.</p>
            <p>For,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>He ruleth by his power for euer.</hi>] Yee righteous, <hi>feare</hi> not the frownes of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, falſly ſo called, the <hi>hatred</hi> of the world, <hi>ſickneſſe, famine, ſword,</hi> or <hi>peſtilence,</hi> the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of mortall men, helliſh <hi>principalities,</hi> or <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> nor any <hi>creature:</hi> for your <hi>God</hi> ruleth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will in the armies of <hi>heauen,</hi> and in the <hi>inhabitants</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.</note> doing whatſoeuer pleaſeth him euery where. Yee wicked, <hi>feare,</hi> and tremble; be full of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and heauineſſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 145.20</note> howle and <hi>lament;</hi> for God <hi>ruleth,</hi> who preſerueth all them that <hi>loue</hi> him: but all ſuch as you are, he <hi>destroyeth:</hi> All yee vngodly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>repent</hi> ſpeedily, for God <hi>ruleth,</hi> who makes all things <hi>worke</hi> together for the beſt to them that <hi>loue</hi> him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.</note> but vpon you he ſhall raine <hi>ſnares, fire,</hi> and <hi>brimstone,</hi> and an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>tempeſt,</hi> this ſhall bee the <hi>portion</hi> of your <hi>cup,</hi> becauſe not chance, nor <hi>fortune,</hi> nor <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets,</hi> nor <hi>windes,</hi> nor <hi>Popes,</hi> nor <hi>hell,</hi> nor <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures rule,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> alone <hi>ruleth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ruleth by his power.</hi>] Ye Potentates, and ſonnes of the <hi>mighty,</hi> lift not vp your <hi>hornes</hi> on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150664:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>high,</hi> oppoſe not your <hi>greatnes</hi> againſt any <hi>ordinance</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> for hee ruleth by his <hi>power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.35, 37.</note> none can ſtay his <hi>hand,</hi> nor may ſay to him, What doeſt thou? Them that walke in their <hi>pride,</hi> hee is able to <hi>abaſe.</hi> Yee <hi>ſinners,</hi> prouoke not him to <hi>anger,</hi> for hee ruleth by his <hi>power;</hi> if yee ſtill forget him, and will not conſider, hee will <hi>teare</hi> you in <hi>pieces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.22.</note> and none can <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer</hi> you. Yee that <hi>feare</hi> him, bee not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, becauſe your <hi>enemies</hi> are too <hi>ſtrong</hi> for you: doubt not of <hi>reliefe,</hi> becauſe your <hi>miſery</hi> ſeemes helpleſſe: <hi>deſpaire</hi> not of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, becauſe you ſee no <hi>remedy:</hi> for your <hi>God</hi> not onely <hi>ruleth,</hi> but he ruleth by his <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> euen by his mighty <hi>power,</hi> whereby hee is <hi>able</hi> to <hi>ſubdue</hi> all things to <hi>himſelfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.20.</note> euen by his infinite <hi>power,</hi> whereby hee is <hi>able</hi> to doe exceeding abundantly for you, beyond all that you can <hi>aske,</hi> or thinke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For euer.</hi>] Thinke not, O ye <hi>wicked,</hi> that there is any time, wherein you ſhall haue the rule in your <hi>hands,</hi> or ſhall eſcape his <hi>iudgements;</hi> for hee <hi>ruleth</hi> for euer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.34.</note> his <hi>dominion</hi> is an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting <hi>dominion,</hi> and of his <hi>kingdome</hi> there is no end. <hi>Reioyce,</hi> O yee <hi>righteous,</hi> for the <hi>proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> the <hi>goodnes,</hi> the <hi>protection,</hi> the <hi>preſence,</hi> the <hi>power,</hi> the <hi>iuſtice,</hi> the <hi>mercy</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God</hi> ſhall neuer bee <hi>diminiſhed,</hi> ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150664:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150664:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150664:16"/>
               <hi>ceaſe,</hi> ſhall neuer <hi>faile</hi> you; for hee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by his <hi>power</hi> for euer:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 146.10.</note> Thy <hi>God,</hi> O <hi>Sion, raigneth,</hi> and he ſhall <hi>raigne</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His eyes behold the nations.</hi>] O yee mad <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.15.</note> that ſeeke out deepe <hi>deuices</hi> to hide your <hi>counſels</hi> from the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to keepe your <hi>workes</hi> ſecret in darke, asking, Who ſeeth vs? Who can <hi>know</hi> vs? woe bee vnto you: for his <hi>eyes behold</hi> the <hi>Nations;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.11.</note> hell,</hi> and <hi>deſtruction</hi> are before <hi>him;</hi> how much more the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>children</hi> of men? hee hath ſeene all your <hi>imaginations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 10.14.</note> he beholdeth all your <hi>miſchiefe</hi> and ſpite to requite it with his owne <hi>hand.</hi> Ye faithfull <hi>ones,</hi> be the ſame in all places, and in all <hi>countries,</hi> diſſemble no where, ſinne no where; for your <hi>God</hi> will find it out, his <hi>eyes</hi> behold all <hi>Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.13.</note> hee beholdeth all the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men, his <hi>eyes</hi> are vpon all the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 34.21.</note> and hee ſeeth his <hi>goings;</hi> his <hi>eyes</hi> are in euery <hi>place</hi> beholding both the <hi>euill</hi> and the <hi>good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 15.3.</note> You that are in <hi>affliction,</hi> doe not ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.27.</note> My <hi>way</hi> is hid from <hi>God:</hi> but be <hi>glad,</hi> and reioyce in his <hi>mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.7.</note> in the midſt of thy <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> with full <hi>aſſurance</hi> that hee conſiders thy <hi>trouble,</hi> and knowes thy <hi>ſoule</hi> in aduerſities; for his eyes behold the <hi>Nations,</hi> and his eye-<hi>lids</hi> do try the <hi>children</hi> of men:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28.</note> there is no ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his <hi>vnderstanding: Behold,</hi> his <hi>eye</hi> is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150664:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon them that <hi>feare</hi> him, and that <hi>hope</hi> in his <hi>mercy,</hi> to deliuer their <hi>ſoule</hi> from <hi>death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.19.</note> and to keepe them <hi>aliue</hi> in <hi>famine.</hi> All <hi>people</hi> truſt in the <hi>liuing Lord</hi> of <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>earth,</hi> haue him alone to bee your <hi>God,</hi> for hee is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>God:</hi> The Heathen gods haue <hi>eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.5.</note> and ſee not;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</note> but our <hi>God</hi> ſeeth euery <hi>thing</hi> that hee hath made, and his <hi>eyes</hi> behold all <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let not the rebellious exalt themſelues: they which are rebellious, let them not bee lifted vp too much in themſelues.</hi>] Pray for this vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo oft as you heare of <hi>Nations</hi> rebelling againſt any <hi>Chriſtian Countrey;</hi> for hee alone is <hi>able</hi> to tame, and <hi>ſpoyle</hi> the ſtout-<hi>hearted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.</note> and can cauſe the men of <hi>might</hi> to haue no <hi>ſtrength</hi> in their <hi>hands. Pray</hi> for this vnto him, ſo oft as you ſee any proud <hi>perſons</hi> exalt themſelues againſt the free paſſage of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20</note> for hee alone is able to bruiſe <hi>Satan</hi> himſelfe, and to tread him <hi>downe</hi> vnder our <hi>feete.</hi> Pray for this vnto him, when the <hi>enemy</hi> waxeth ſtil prouder; for though he <hi>ſuffer</hi> them ſometime to <hi>afflict</hi> vs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.27</note> yet hee cannot abide that they ſhould behaue <hi>themſelues</hi> proudly, and ſtrangely againſt vs. <hi>Pray</hi> for this vnto him, euen when thy <hi>ſonnes</hi> and <hi>daughters</hi> are arrogant and <hi>inſolent:</hi> for he will either <hi>breake</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150664:17"/>them, becauſe they are <hi>rebellious,</hi> or if they <hi>belong</hi> to him, hee will <hi>heale</hi> their rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O bleſſe our God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 48.</note> yee people, and make the voyce of his praiſe to be heard.</hi>] Gods <hi>holy</hi> ones are ſo <hi>affected</hi> with deſire to <hi>praiſe</hi> him, as they prouoke all other alſo to <hi>praiſe</hi> him. Haue you no deſire to praiſe <hi>God?</hi> Oh, how can you aske any <hi>mercy</hi> at his <hi>hands?</hi> Is your deſire to <hi>praiſe</hi> him ſo weake, as it <hi>moues</hi> you not to draw <hi>others</hi> to this <hi>duty?</hi> Oh, how little reckoning make you of <hi>God,</hi> and of his <hi>glory?</hi> and how careleſſe are you of others <hi>ſaluation?</hi> Doe you prouoke <hi>others</hi> to diſhonour and <hi>blaſpheme</hi> him? Oh, you doe an <hi>abominable</hi> thing; ſuch a wickedneſſe, as <hi>neuer</hi> did wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Idolaters</hi> to their <hi>falſe</hi> gods. <hi>Beware</hi> of no <hi>affection:</hi> beware of too little <hi>affection,</hi> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to this high <hi>affection</hi> vnto the <hi>praiſe</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which will moue you to <hi>exhort</hi> others to it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.3.</note> ſaying, O <hi>magnifie</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> with mee, and let vs <hi>exalt</hi> his <hi>Name</hi> together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our God.</hi>] This is the <hi>glory</hi> of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath made them ſo neere vnto him as they may very boldly <hi>profeſſe,</hi> and call him, <hi>Our God.</hi> Oh yee <hi>hypocrites,</hi> this <hi>glory</hi> doth not <hi>belong</hi> to you: if you call him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.21.</note> Our <hi>God,</hi> hee denyeth it, ſaying, Away
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150664:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>from me, yee <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>iniquitie,</hi> I know you not. Oh, you <hi>enemies</hi> to the true <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> this <hi>glory</hi> doth not belong to you; if you call him, Our <hi>God,</hi> he denyeth it, ſaying, Not I, but your <hi>belly</hi> is your <hi>god,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.19.</note> and your end <hi>damnation.</hi> Oh you <hi>worldlings,</hi> this <hi>glory</hi> belongs not to you, <hi>ignorant, blind,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuing <hi>ſoules:</hi> if you call him, Our <hi>God,</hi> he denyeth it, ſaying, Not I,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> but the <hi>Deuill</hi> is your <hi>god.</hi> But, oh yee <hi>ſeruants</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to you, euen to you doth this <hi>glory</hi> belong, if you call him, Our <hi>God,</hi> he denyeth it not, but anſwereth, I am the <hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10.</note> and you are my <hi>people.</hi> All that deſire this <hi>glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.23.</note> bee his true <hi>ſeruants,</hi> be in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> bee in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with his <hi>Church,</hi> then may you ſay alſo, The <hi>Lord</hi> is Our <hi>God,</hi> euen our owne God:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.</note> then are you <hi>bleſſed,</hi> Oh bleſſed are the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> whoſe God is the Lord.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> Then are you <hi>protected.</hi> If God bee on our <hi>ſide,</hi> who can bee againſt vs? Then are you <hi>ſafe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.14.</note> Our God will be our <hi>guide</hi> euen vnto <hi>death.</hi> Reioyce that the Lord is become your God, prepare an <hi>habitation</hi> for him in your <hi>hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.2.</note> exalt him with your tongues, and call to others, ſaying, Bleſſe our God, <hi>bleſſe</hi> our God, O ye people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And make the voyce of his praiſe to bee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150664:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150664:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150664:19"/>heard.</hi>] This is the token that people are come vnto God, when they make <hi>others</hi> heare them <hi>praiſe</hi> God: they that make <hi>others</hi> heare them praiſe Images, and ſuperſtitious <hi>Popiſh</hi> Ceremonies, ſhew no token that they are come vnto God: they that make others heare them praiſe the ſinfull pleaſures of wicked luſt, ſhew no token that they are come vnto God: they that make others heare them, by <hi>ſwearing,</hi> and <hi>lying,</hi> and other ſinnes, <hi>blaſpheme</hi> God, ſhew no <hi>token</hi> of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto him: they that are <hi>afraid,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to let others heare them <hi>profeſſe,</hi> praiſe, and <hi>glorifie</hi> God, ſhew no <hi>token</hi> that they are come vnto him. But they that with <hi>zeale,</hi> modeſtie, <hi>reuerence,</hi> and ſinceritie doe make others heare, and perceiue that they doe <hi>acknowledge,</hi> honour, and <hi>praiſe</hi> God, doe ſhew a ſufficient <hi>token</hi> that they are indeed come vnto him. Therefore, when the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of praiſing God are performing, congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate together readily thereto, lurke no where in Kitchin, or Hall, or Butterie, or Chamber, or Yard, or Street, or any where abſent, which is enough to make you ſuſpected of irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearts. But come forth all, &amp; come affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and come prepared to pray together, to heare together, and to ſing together, that we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150664:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>may together bleſſe our God, and make the voice of his glorious praiſe heard, euen his praiſe, <hi>[Which holdeth our ſoule in life.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9.</note> Euen his praiſe, <hi>which hath reſtored our ſoulevnto life:</hi> The reſtoring of our ſoules vnto life, &amp; the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in <hi>life,</hi> are ſpeciall <hi>reaſons</hi> to lead vs to <hi>praiſe God.</hi> Oh man, or woman, whoſe ſoule by <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> or by the malice of <hi>enemies,</hi> or by other <hi>euils</hi> hath been compaſſed about with the ſorrowes of <hi>hell,</hi> and beene in the ſnares of <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> of his maruellous <hi>goodneſſe</hi> hath redeemed it, and reſtored vnto <hi>life,</hi> and doth ſtill <hi>preſerue,</hi> and keepe thee <hi>healthfull,</hi> and <hi>aliue:</hi> Doeſt thou <hi>diſobey</hi> this good <hi>God?</hi> doeſt thou <hi>diſhonour</hi> him with thy <hi>life?</hi> doeſt thou <hi>ſinne</hi> againſt him with the <hi>health</hi> and libertie that hee giues thee? doeſt thou not <hi>praiſe</hi> him for his <hi>wonderfull</hi> kindneſſe? O <hi>fooliſh</hi> body, and vnwiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6.</note> doe you thus requite the <hi>Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O ye righteous, be it farre from you to be ſo <hi>vngracious:</hi> doe not you ſo requite the <hi>Lord;</hi> but remember all his <hi>benefits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.</note> thinke vpon all his <hi>goodneſse,</hi> and conſider in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, how when your <hi>ſoules</hi> were in wofull <hi>miſerie,</hi> when your <hi>liues</hi> were in great <hi>ieopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> your troubles were <hi>ſore,</hi> and many, hee heard your <hi>cry,</hi> hee ſent you <hi>helpe</hi> from his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150664:20"/>
               <hi>holy</hi> place, and hee redeemed you from all your <hi>miſeries;</hi> and it is he only which holdeth our ſoule in life, and</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suffereth not our feet to be moued.</hi>] They that doe ſerue <hi>God</hi> faithfully, are in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>ſafetie.</hi> Yee bloudie and <hi>deceitfull</hi> men, why doe you imagine <hi>miſchiefe</hi> againſt <hi>Gods</hi> faithfull <hi>ſeruants?</hi> They ſhall bee as Mount <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.1.</note> which cannot bee <hi>remoned.</hi> Yee gates of <hi>hell,</hi> why doe you offer violence to <hi>Gods Saints?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.29.</note> They are in his hands, who is greater then all, and none can plucke them out. Ye men on <hi>earth</hi> that deſire to be ſafe, why doe yee not <hi>turne</hi> from your <hi>ſinnes,</hi> and come to our <hi>God</hi> to <hi>ſerue</hi> him? Then you ſhall bee <hi>ſafe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</note> and ſhall <hi>neuer</hi> bee <hi>mooued.</hi> Yee <hi>righteous,</hi> why are you afraid in any condition, or for any mans threatning? <hi>Feare</hi> not,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22.</note> 
               <hi>faint</hi> not, caſt your <hi>burthen</hi> vpon the <hi>Lord,</hi> hee will <hi>ſuſtaine</hi> you, and will neuer <hi>ſuffer</hi> you to bee <hi>moued.</hi> Are we <hi>ſafe?</hi> Is our <hi>King ſafe?</hi> Is the Kings <hi>ſonne</hi> ſafe? Is our Land <hi>ſafe?</hi> Are our <hi>Preachers,</hi> and <hi>people ſafe?</hi> Are our <hi>wiues,</hi> and children <hi>ſafe?</hi> Are our <hi>goods</hi> and cattel <hi>ſafe?</hi> Giue <hi>God</hi> alone the <hi>glory,</hi> ſing praiſe to his <hi>Name:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6.44.4, 6, 7.</note> for hee onely <hi>ſaueth</hi> vs, he preſerueth man, and beaſt: Not our owne arme, nor our ſword, but hee himſelfe hath
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150664:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſaued</hi> vs from all our <hi>enemies,</hi> putting them to <hi>ſhame</hi> that <hi>hated</hi> vs:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 18.34.56.13.</note> hee inlargeth our <hi>ſteps</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, hee holdeth our <hi>feet</hi> that they <hi>ſlip</hi> not, hee keepes them from <hi>falling,</hi> he ſets them,
<note place="margin">40.3.</note> as on a <hi>Rocke,</hi> and ſuffers them not to bee <hi>moued;</hi> and if at any time,
<note place="margin">30.6, 7.</note> to <hi>checke</hi> vs for our <hi>ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and vaine confidence, wee be <hi>moued,</hi> and troubled, it is onely his gracious triall of vs, that wee might then looke to him, and ſay to him, In this alſo wee acknowledge thine hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For thou, O God, haſt prooued vs:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 10.</note> thou haſt tryed vs, as Siluer is tryed.</hi>] Gods children can picke matter of <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> and of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation out of their <hi>affliction.</hi> O thou that quarrelleſt at the <hi>godlies</hi> Religion, becauſe of their <hi>tribulation,</hi> and <hi>ſcoffeſt</hi> at their <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> becauſe of their <hi>affliction:</hi> their <hi>croſſe</hi> is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thy <hi>crowne;</hi> their <hi>miſcrie,</hi> then thy <hi>proſperitie;</hi> their <hi>ſorrowes,</hi> then thy <hi>pleaſures.</hi> For thou pickeſt out of thine <hi>abundance,</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of irreligion, of <hi>pride,</hi> of <hi>vnthankfulneſſe,</hi> of <hi>crueltie,</hi> of <hi>condemnation:</hi> but they out of their ſore <hi>affliction,</hi> matter of <hi>reioycing,</hi> of <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> and of <hi>conſolation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> O <hi>child</hi> of God, whoſe mind is grieued, who art pricked in thy <hi>reines,</hi> whoſe <hi>fleſh,</hi> and whoſe <hi>heart</hi> fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth becauſe of <hi>rebuke,</hi> and <hi>chaſtening;</hi> be no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150664:21"/>more ſo <hi>fooliſh,</hi> ſo ignorant, and ſo like a <hi>beaſt</hi> before the <hi>Lord,</hi> regard and take out this <hi>leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> picke thou matter of <hi>comfort,</hi> and of <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> out of thine <hi>affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here muſt be grace, wiſedome, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and obſeruation: Firſt, grace; for if we be by <hi>faith</hi> in Chriſt entred into that <hi>grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2, 3</note> wherein wee ſtand vnder <hi>hope</hi> of Gods <hi>glory,</hi> then ſhall wee euen glory in <hi>tribulations.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>wiſedome;</hi> for if we be truely <hi>wiſe,</hi> we ſhall vnderſtand the eaſie and wealthy <hi>place</hi> of the vngodly to be ſo <hi>ſlippery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.18.</note> and their end ſuch <hi>infelicitie,</hi> and ſo vnhappy, as wee ſhall praiſe God that wee <hi>drinke</hi> not of their full <hi>cup</hi> of proſperitie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26.</note> and preferre the <hi>affliction</hi> of Gods <hi>people,</hi> before their ſinfull and <hi>ſhort</hi> pleaſures; eſteeming the reproach of <hi>Christ</hi> greater <hi>riches,</hi> then the <hi>treaſures</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>experience;</hi> for if wee find the <hi>tryall</hi> how <hi>God</hi> comforteth vs in all our tribulation;
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</note> yea, ſo farre as hee makes vs <hi>able</hi> to <hi>comfort</hi> them which are in any <hi>trouble,</hi> by the <hi>comfort</hi> wherewith wee our ſelues are comforted of <hi>him,</hi> we ſhall get much <hi>ioy,</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> and <hi>bleſse</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> with great <hi>gladneſſe.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation;</hi> for if we obſerue, firſt, Who <hi>afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> vs, namely, our faithfull <hi>Creatour,</hi> our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Father,</hi> our owne <hi>God,</hi> who may <hi>iustly</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150664:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.3.</note> What vnkindneſſe haue I <hi>euer done</hi> vnto you? Wherein haue I been any way <hi>grieuous</hi> vnto you?
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.31.</note> I haue beene alway a <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>mercies</hi> vnto you; a <hi>God</hi> of all <hi>comfort</hi> vnto you. I am the <hi>Father</hi> of ſpirits,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</note> to whom you ought to be in <hi>ſubiection,</hi> much rather then to the <hi>fathers</hi> of your fleſh. Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.8.</note> How he <hi>dealeth</hi> with vs when hee <hi>afflicteth</hi> vs, namely, hee therein <hi>dealeth</hi> with vs, as with <hi>ſonnes;</hi> not as with <hi>baſtards,</hi> whoſe-fathers are <hi>aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> to haue them vnder their <hi>nurture;</hi> but, as with <hi>naturall,</hi> and legitimate <hi>children,</hi> whom the <hi>parents</hi> nouriſh and chaſten.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Out of what <hi>affection</hi> he af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>licteth vs, namely, out of his moſt <hi>fatherly</hi> loue.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.12.</note> For whom he <hi>loueth,</hi> he <hi>chaſteneth,</hi> euen as a <hi>father</hi> doth that <hi>ſonne</hi> in whom he <hi>delighteth.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, His ordinary entring of vs into his <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and into his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which is by <hi>afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> For euery <hi>ſonne,</hi> whom he receiueth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.7.</note> he <hi>ſcourgeth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22</note> and through much <hi>tribulation</hi> wee muſt enter into his <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Fifthly, How he <hi>afflicteth</hi> vs, namely, in <hi>meaſure,</hi> with ſuch <hi>moderation,</hi> and mingling of <hi>mercy</hi> with <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as, though we be ſore <hi>chaſtened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 118.18</note> yet wee are not <hi>killed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22.</note> though we be ſharpely correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet we are not <hi>conſumed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> though the <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> be long, or great, yet we be made able
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150664:22"/>to <hi>beare</hi> it. Sixthly, What he doth in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs, namely, hee <hi>proueth</hi> vs, hee doth not <hi>prouoke</hi> vs like the <hi>Tempter,</hi> but proueth vs like a <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.2.</note> that he may <hi>know,</hi> or that rather he may make it <hi>knowne</hi> to our <hi>ſelues,</hi> and to our <hi>friends</hi> that <hi>ioy</hi> at it, and to our <hi>foes</hi> that <hi>gnaſh</hi> their <hi>teeth</hi> at it, what is in our <hi>hearts,</hi> and what care, and <hi>conſtancy</hi> there is in vs to keepe his <hi>commandements.</hi> Seuenthly, To what <hi>end</hi> he <hi>afflicteth</hi> vs, namely, to our profit, and to doe vs <hi>good;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10 <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.16. <hi>&amp; ver.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12</note> as to <hi>purge</hi> vs: to <hi>humble</hi> vs: to take <hi>away</hi> our <hi>ſinne:</hi> to <hi>nurture</hi> vs: to draw vs to <hi>himſelfe:</hi> to <hi>ſaue</hi> vs from the <hi>condemnation</hi> of this <hi>world:</hi> to make vs partakers of his owne <hi>holineſſe:</hi> and to fit vs to <hi>raigne</hi> with him in his Kingdome. Eightthly, How he <hi>eſteemeth</hi> vs, in afflicting vs, namely, not as hee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the <hi>wicked,</hi> whom hee taketh away from the <hi>earth</hi> like <hi>droſse:</hi> but as hee eſteemeth his Saints, whom hee keepeth vnder his owne <hi>wings,</hi> and in his owne <hi>hand,</hi> as <hi>precious gold:</hi> not as refuſe <hi>ſiluer,</hi> which he reiecteth; but as fine <hi>ſiluer,</hi> which hee hath <hi>tryed,</hi> and fined for his owne <hi>vſe.</hi> If wee obſerue all <hi>theſe,</hi> who ſeeth not that we may <hi>picke</hi> out matter of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation,</hi> and <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> out of our <hi>affliction,</hi> and <hi>reioyce</hi> that wee are <hi>able</hi> to ſay, Thou, O <hi>God,</hi> haſt proued vs, thou haſt tryed vs, as <hi>ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150664:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>is tryed: thou haſt <hi>magniſied</hi> vs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 7.17, 18</note> in ſetting thine <hi>heart</hi> vpon vs, to <hi>viſit</hi> vs euery <hi>morning,</hi> and to try vs euery <hi>moment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou broughteſt vs into the net:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.12.</note> thou laydſt affliction vpon our loynes: Thou haſt cauſed men to ride ouer our heads: we went throrow fire, and thorow water.</hi>] God doth ofttimes <hi>exerciſe</hi> his very <hi>deare</hi> children with very <hi>ſore,</hi> and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>affliction.</hi> Art thou afflicted, O <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> Looke vnto <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> did: as <hi>Dauid</hi> did:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 1.21. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 118.18. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.12.</note> as <hi>Daniel</hi> did: as heere the <hi>godly</hi> did: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it to be hee that hath <hi>brought</hi> thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, that hath <hi>laid</hi> it vpon thee, that hath <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> men to doe it, conſider it <hi>wiſely:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</note> ſubmit thy ſelfe to it <hi>quietly:</hi> take it reuerently: <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> it thankfully, and <hi>beare</hi> it conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> though thou <hi>know</hi> thine owne <hi>innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> for ſo he <hi>exerciſeth</hi> oft times his <hi>deare,</hi> and his <hi>righteous</hi> children.</p>
            <p>Art thou his <hi>obedient</hi> child?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 1.8. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17.</note> thinke it not <hi>ſtrange,</hi> be not diſcomforted that thou art <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: Iob</hi> righteous: <hi>Dauid</hi> a man after his owne <hi>heart: Daniel,</hi> beloued: <hi>Paul,</hi> a choſen veſſell: <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his onely <hi>Sonne,</hi> in whom hee is well <hi>pleaſed:</hi> yet all theſe he <hi>ſorely</hi> afflicted. Being ſo; O <hi>ncere</hi> Chriſtian, vnder his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, admire his <hi>wiſedome:</hi> thinke of the <hi>lot</hi> of thy fellow <hi>brethren: care</hi> not for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150664:23"/>vpbraiding: <hi>indure</hi> the vncharitables cenſuring: and refreſh thine <hi>heart</hi> with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, though, being one of his <hi>children,</hi> thou ſuffer <hi>ſore</hi> affliction.</p>
            <p>How <hi>ſore</hi> is it, when he caſteth vs as down on the <hi>ground,</hi> and (as it were) throweth vs along vnder the moſt vile <hi>contempt</hi> of men, ſetting euen <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and Sycophants (as it were) to tread and <hi>trample</hi> vpon vs, and to make vs no better then as myre vnder their very <hi>horſes</hi> feet: exalting them on high <hi>aboue</hi> vs, and bringing vs to moſt <hi>low</hi> and baſe eſtate:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dout.</hi> 28.43, 44.</note> and vs the <hi>tayle?</hi> when he puts vs to the hardeſt pinches, <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>perils</hi> that can bee, and driueth vs thorow the moſt <hi>grieuous</hi> extremities, and moſt <hi>feareful</hi> calamities, to make vs as <hi>hopleſse</hi> to eſcape, as they are the <hi>burning</hi> that paſſe <hi>thorow</hi> a violent <hi>fire;</hi> or they drowning, that goe thorow a deepe <hi>gulfe</hi> of water? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O beloued Chriſtian, art thou in any affliction?
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.3, 5.</note> thinke it no <hi>newes;</hi> thinke it not thine alone <hi>caſe;</hi> thinke it not <hi>ſtrange;</hi> be not <hi>weary</hi> of it; do not <hi>faint; diſtruſt</hi> not; <hi>deſpaire</hi> not:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25</note> ſing in thy <hi>priſon;</hi> reioyce in thy <hi>dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> refuſe not to take <hi>comfort;</hi> yea, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy <hi>leſſon;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>God,</hi> euen our moſt gracious <hi>God,</hi> oft
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150664:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>times doth exerciſe his very <hi>deare</hi> children with very great affliction: and not onely ſo, but alſo with manifold affliction;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> afflictions of the <hi>bodie</hi> by aches, <hi>paines,</hi> ſickneſſes, diuers <hi>diſeaſes;</hi> afflictions of the <hi>name,</hi> by infamies, <hi>reproches,</hi> and all bad <hi>reports:</hi> affliction of the <hi>goods,</hi> by loſſes, by <hi>thefts,</hi> by <hi>robberies,</hi> by <hi>debts,</hi> by ſundry <hi>caſualties:</hi> affliction of the <hi>mind,</hi> by <hi>terrors,</hi> by <hi>feares,</hi> by <hi>diſcontentments,</hi> by <hi>diſcomforts</hi> in <hi>husband,</hi> or in <hi>wife,</hi> or in <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> or in <hi>ſeruants,</hi> or in <hi>neighbours,</hi> or in <hi>friends:</hi> affliction of euery <hi>kind,</hi> nets to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare</hi> vs, burthens to <hi>oppreſſe</hi> vs, men to <hi>tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize</hi> ouer vs, <hi>fire</hi> to burne vs, <hi>water</hi> to drowne vs.</p>
            <p>O Chriſtian <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>woman,</hi> is thine afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not onely <hi>ſore,</hi> but alſo manifold? Fret not thy ſelfe for all this:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.8.</note> conſent not in any <hi>wiſe</hi> to do <hi>euill:</hi> forget not <hi>Gods</hi> Name:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17, 18, 20.</note> deale not <hi>falſly</hi> in his Couenant: let not thine <hi>heart</hi> turne backe, nor thy <hi>ſteps</hi> decline from his <hi>way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35, 36, 37, 38.</note> nor ſtretch out thine <hi>hands</hi> to a ſtrange <hi>god:</hi> caſt not <hi>away</hi> thy <hi>confidence:</hi> liue by <hi>faith</hi> patiently and <hi>ioyfully;</hi> and to this end remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that thy confidence hath great <hi>recompence</hi> of <hi>reward:</hi> remember, that after long <hi>patience,</hi> thou ſhalt receiue the <hi>promiſe:</hi> remember, that many are the <hi>troubles</hi> of the <hi>righteous:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150664:24"/>that yet a <hi>little</hi> while, and hee that ſhall come, will <hi>come,</hi> and will not <hi>tarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely, ſee thou bee not the <hi>cauſe</hi> of thine owne affliction, as wicked <hi>ſinners</hi> are, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of the <hi>wicked</hi> are,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.20. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30 <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.17</note> and as careleſſe Chriſtians are: for then thou art a <hi>foole;</hi> then thy beſt comfort in thine affliction is to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> of thy <hi>tranſgreſsion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.16.</note> and to craue <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Againe, ſee that thou <hi>deſire</hi> not afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for though <hi>God</hi> pleaſe to <hi>ſend</hi> it, he will cauſe it to <hi>worke</hi> to thy beſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> yet if thou wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>deſire</hi> it, hee may leaue thee to thy <hi>ſelfe,</hi> and ſo thou wilt peruert it to thy worſt: it ſhewes <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> wiſely to <hi>beare</hi> it; but ſhewes <hi>arrogancy</hi> and vaine <hi>confidence,</hi> to deſire it. Alſo <hi>maruell</hi> not, that <hi>God</hi> exerciſeth his children oft times with <hi>ſore</hi> affliction, when they would faine be in <hi>liberty</hi> and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for it is his <hi>will:</hi> and who ſhould haue their <hi>will;</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> or the <hi>Child?</hi> Parents ought to ſhew, and mainetaine their owne <hi>right will</hi> againſt the <hi>childs</hi> wicked, or <hi>wanton will;</hi> yea, though the child doe pet at it, and bee ſicke at it, &amp;c. Otherwiſe (as lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table experience ſhewes) the childs wills ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling, is the parents ſhame, ſmart, paine, and vndoing. Now our heauenly Father, whoſe will is moſt holy, and who knoweth that his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150664:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>childrens willed liberty, and wiſhed free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would bee many times abuſed to his diſhonour, therefore chuſeth rather to his glory and their good, to croſſe their indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and childiſh will in denying them eaſe, and freedome; &amp; to do his owne will in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing them with ſore affliction.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.18.</note> O behold his <hi>goodneſse</hi> and <hi>wiſedome</hi> herein! for all this is that he may haue the fitteſt <hi>occaſion</hi> to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious vnto <hi>vs:</hi> this he euen waiteth for, and this theſe holy ones ſo experienced, as they haue left a worthy <hi>confeſsion</hi> of it, ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But at length thou broughteſt vs into a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy place.</hi>] After God hath tryed his children by <hi>affliction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.9.</note> hee bringeth them out into the wayes of <hi>conſolation:</hi> hee <hi>afflicteth</hi> them, hee <hi>childeth</hi> them, hee is <hi>angry</hi> with them, hee bringeth them into the <hi>Net,</hi> hee <hi>aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> them, hee commits them to the <hi>fire,</hi> he caſts them into the <hi>water,</hi> he doth try them by <hi>affliction,</hi> but not alwayes. Oh afflicted Chriſtian, be <hi>patient,</hi> though the <hi>Rod</hi> of the wicked come vpon thee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.25</note> it ſhall not reſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee: be <hi>content,</hi> though thou be in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thy trouble ſhall not laſt euer: bee <hi>cheerefull,</hi> though thou be in pouerty, in debt, in miſery, thou ſhalt come out: bee of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150664:25"/>though it be long,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.18.</note> yet there will bee an end, and thy hope ſhall not bee cut off: bee <hi>thankefull,</hi> and waite ſtill on God, and let thy Soule keepe ſilence vnto him.</p>
            <p>For after he hath tryed his Children by <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi> he bringeth them into the wayes of <hi>conſolation,</hi> hee his owne ſelfe doth it: hee brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.10.</note> Ioſeph</hi> out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Dauid</hi> out of all his troubles; theſe out of the Net, out of the Fire, out of the Water: and he his owne ſelfe brings all his Children out of their <hi>affliction.</hi> O thou good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, whom God hath brought into any grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous condition,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.2.</note> euen as the eyes of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant looke to receiue helpe from the hand of his owne Maſter, and as the eyes of the Maiden are lifted vp to the hand of her owne Miſtreſſe: So lift vp thine eyes, and expect deliuerance from Gods owne <hi>ſelfe:</hi> hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath <hi>wounded</hi> thee, and he himſelfe will <hi>heale</hi> thee: he himſelfe hath <hi>caſt</hi> thee downe, and he himſelfe will <hi>raiſe</hi> thee vp.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not neede to cry to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in Heauen or in Earth: Oh who will <hi>helpe</hi> mee? Who will <hi>heale</hi> mee? Who will <hi>comfort</hi> me? Who will <hi>deliuer</hi> me? for hee <hi>Himſelfe</hi> will do it: as in <hi>afflicting</hi> thee, hee giues not his Authority to another: ſo in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſing</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:150664:25"/>thee, he will not giue his <hi>glory</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Reioyce in the <hi>Net</hi> he hath brought thee into; reioyce in the <hi>affliction</hi> he hath laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy loynes; reioyce in the <hi>riding</hi> of men ouer thine head; reioyce in the <hi>fire</hi> ready to burne thee, and in the <hi>water</hi> ready to drowne thee, for he <hi>himſelfe</hi> will bring thee out, euen he, to whoſe <hi>helpe</hi> thou maiſt moſt confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truſt. Vaine is the <hi>helpe</hi> of Man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.11.</note> but hee is a ſure <hi>Helper,</hi> he is a ſure <hi>deliuerer,</hi> he is a ſure <hi>comforter;</hi> his power is a ſure <hi>power,</hi> his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe is a ſure <hi>willingneſſe,</hi> his promiſe is a ſure <hi>promiſe,</hi> his mercies are ſure <hi>mercies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</note> they ſhall not be aſhamed that <hi>waite</hi> on him, they ſhal not be forſaken that <hi>ſeek</hi> him, he wil neuer <hi>faile</hi> them that <hi>truſt</hi> in him: but after, for his owne <hi>glory</hi> and their good, he hath <hi>tryed</hi> them ſome while by <hi>affliction,</hi> he will in due time, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in due time, bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out into <hi>conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Chriſtian, though yet thou bee chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euery morning, do not ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 73.13.</note> I haue waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mine <hi>hands</hi> in Innocency, and <hi>clenſed</hi> mine <hi>heart</hi> in vaine: do not not ſay, The Lord hath <hi>forgotten</hi> to be merciful: do not ſay,
<note place="margin">116.11.</note> They that <hi>prophecy</hi> of future <hi>comfort</hi> vnto thee, are Lyers: do not ſay, thy way is hidden from the Lord:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.27.</note> doe not ſay, thy <hi>Iudgement</hi> is paſſed ouer of thy God:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11.</note> but <hi>beleeue</hi> that light is ſowne for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150664:26"/>the <hi>Righteous,</hi> and gladneſſe for the vpright in <hi>heart,</hi> and in due ſeaſon, ſuch ſhall reape a pleaſant <hi>crop:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 30.5, 11.</note> beleeue that at length he will turne thy mourning into reioycing, and thine heauineſſe into gladneſſe: though <hi>weeping</hi> indure all the night, yet <hi>ioyes</hi> ſhal come in the morning:
<note place="margin">126.5, 6.</note> Though thou doſt now <hi>ſow</hi> in teares, yet hereafter thou ſhalt <hi>reape</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: he will bring thee out of <hi>borrowing,</hi> into the ability for <hi>lending;</hi> out of preſent miſery, into permanent felicity; out of a poore, ſicke, deſolate and dolefull caſe, into a delightfull and wealthy incloſure.</p>
            <p>And when this is not according to thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in Earth, remember the infinit and endleſſe Conſolation prepared, and reſerued for thee in <hi>Heauen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">16.9, 11.</note> and let thine <hi>heart</hi> be <hi>glad,</hi> and thy <hi>glory</hi> reioyce, and thy <hi>fleſh</hi> reſt in hope of that fulneſſe of <hi>ioy,</hi> and of thoſe pleaſures at his right hand for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will goe into thine houſe with burnt Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</note> God deliuering his <hi>people</hi> out of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, moues ſome in particular to greater <hi>zeale</hi> of the duties of <hi>Religion.</hi> Oh ſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety of ſome in <hi>affliction!</hi> they ſeeme full of <hi>Deuotion;</hi> but no ſooner <hi>deliuered,</hi> they returne againe to their vaine <hi>conuerſation:</hi> theſe are euen ſuch as God ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.30.</note> receiue no <hi>correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150664:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are ſuch as haue not vpright <hi>hearts</hi> with him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.37. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.14.</note> they are ſuch as prouoke him to <hi>ſtrike</hi> them no more as his <hi>children,</hi> but let them alone as <hi>baſtards</hi> vnto deſtruction. Oh, happy are we, if we bee not of the <hi>number</hi> of theſe, but of ſuch as in their owne particular are moued to bee more <hi>zealous</hi> in the duties of Religion, after they ſee how comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably God hath brought them out of <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction:</hi> heere is more then common <hi>grace;</hi> for ſuch are very rare; heere is true <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> for after a <hi>wiſe</hi> man is rebuked,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.8.</note> hee will <hi>loue</hi> more: heere is right profiting by <hi>affllic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> for after ſuch are afflicted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.67, 71. <hi>Pſame</hi> 116.12.</note> they learne and keepe Gods Word the better: Here is a thankefull mind indeed: for ſuch are <hi>zealous</hi> of Gods <hi>praiſe;</hi> ſuch ſtudy what to render vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; ſuch deſire to expreſſe their <hi>thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſse</hi> in the preſence of all Gods people; ſuch make haſte to meet the Lord in his <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> ſaying euen to himſelfe, <hi>I will goe into thine Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh man and woman, that art willing to go into the Tauerne, and into the Ale-houſe, but vnwilling to goe into Gods Houſe: How fooliſh art thou to goe like the euill ſeruant,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49.</note> to eate and drinke with the drunken, and to ſit among Hypocriticall Scoffers, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150664:27"/>to goe like the Seruants of God to his Houſe, to ſing and pray with his Children, and to heare his holy Miniſters? Oh thou that art willing to goe into the gaming houſe, but not into Gods Houſe! How fooliſh art thou to goe like the ding-thrift, to ſpend the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time, and thy needfull goods with the prophane, vnto thy vndooing, and to refuſe to go like the Prudent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.23.</note> to buy the truth, and get grace vnto health, and wealth, and ſaluation? Oh thou that art willing to goe into the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots houſe, but not into Gods Houſe! How fooliſh art thou to goe like a Foole to the Stockes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 7.22.</note> and like an Oxe to the ſlaughter, vnto the houſe that leadeth to death, and to refuſe to goe like the Wiſe and Religious, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Houſe that leadeth vnto Happineſſe, Comfort, and eternall Life?</p>
            <p>Oh man or woman that art willing to goe into Gods <hi>Houſe,</hi> that loueſt the <hi>place</hi> where his Honour dwelleth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 84.1, 2.</note> that holdeſt his <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles</hi> amiable, that feeleſt thy <hi>ſoule</hi> longing, and fainting for the <hi>Courts</hi> of the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.1</note> that art glad to heare and ſee others willing to go vnto his Houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4.</note> that deſireſt to <hi>dwell</hi> all the dayes of thy life in his Houſe; how prudent and how wiſe art thou? for there thou ſhalt behold the <hi>beauty</hi> of the Lord, enquire at his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150664:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.4, 11.</note> heare the happy tydings of <hi>peace</hi> and of good things, be ſatisfied with <hi>goodneſse,</hi> be euer prayſing of God; there God will be the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>Shield</hi> vnto thee; there he will giue thee <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5.</note> there he will feede thy <hi>Soule</hi> with better then <hi>marrow</hi> and <hi>fatneſse,</hi> there will he hide thee in his <hi>Pauilion,</hi> and in the ſecret of his <hi>Tabernacle</hi> in the time of trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With burnt Offerings will I goe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 13.15.</note> I will offer vnto thee burnt Sacrifices of fat Rammes, with Incenſe: I will prepare Bullocks with Goates in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance.</hi>] The godly worſhip God perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, rightly, delightfully, and plenteouſly: Perſonally, for they come, and they <hi>offer</hi> in their owne <hi>perſons:</hi> Rightly, for they offer to God that which he preſcribeth, then Legall, now Euangelicall <hi>Sacrifices:</hi> Delightfully, for they offer with <hi>Incenſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 30.34.</note> with artificiall &amp; moſt pleaſant perſume of ſweete <hi>Spices:</hi> vnder the Law, with ſpirituall moſt pleaſant perfume of Chriſts moſt ſweete <hi>interceſſion,</hi> and of the moſt ſweete <hi>grace</hi> of his <hi>Spirit</hi> vnder the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell:</hi> Plenteouſly, for they offer not a Ramme,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 29.21.</note> or a Bullocke, or a Goate, but Rammes, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes, and Goates, many <hi>Offrings</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Sacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O you that come not to appeare before
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150664:28"/>the <hi>Lord</hi> in the aſſemblies of his people per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally: how ſawcie and vnreuerent is this? Not a pretended neceſſitie, to ride out to ſee your <hi>purchaſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18, 19, 20.</note> nor the deſire to goe trie your <hi>yoke</hi> of Oxen newly bought; nor your reaſon to tarry at home with your late wedded <hi>wife,</hi> will ſerue to excuſe it. Oh, you that come, and doe offer, but not rightly, in that you offer not that which he preſcribeth, but your owne fancied repetitions, your owne ſuppoſed good intents: how vniuſt, how vncomely is this?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. 1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 15.23 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.1.</note> This <hi>worſhip,</hi> is a worſhip in vaine: this ſeruice, is a rebellion and ſtubborneneſſe: this <hi>offering,</hi> is a ſacrifice for <hi>fooles:</hi> this doing, is doing of <hi>euill.</hi> Oh, you that <hi>offer,</hi> but not delightfully, not with <hi>incenſe,</hi> not in Chriſts name; not in ſinceritie; not with grace in your <hi>hearts:</hi> how vnprofitable, and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceptable is this? You keepe backe Gods part, his portion, his delight, and ſo (without you <hi>repent</hi>) you ſhall find him another <hi>day,</hi> as <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> partly found him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 10.2.</note> that is, a conſuming <hi>fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hob.</hi> 12.28, 29.</note> Oh, you that come and offer to <hi>God,</hi> but not plentifully, but emptie-<hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> grudgingly, with wearineſſe, and ſnuffing at it, euen ſnuffing at the <hi>pure,</hi> and plentifull <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> diſdaining that hee ſhould bee ſo plenteouſly made known by his <hi>Preachers,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150664:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>and his <hi>Word</hi> ſo powerfully taught by them! how vngodly? how crooked? and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull is this?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8, 10, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.2.</note> The <hi>Lord</hi> holds this a deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his <hi>Name,</hi> and a contemning of his <hi>Table.</hi> Hee hath no pleaſure in ſuch <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> he accepts no ſuch offerings, he reckons ſuch offerers, <hi>deceiuers,</hi> hee curſeth them, and their <hi>bleſsings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, you therefore that feare <hi>God,</hi> follow the example of the godly <hi>Prophet;</hi> come (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially on the <hi>Sabbaths</hi>) and appeare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally before the <hi>Lord,</hi> to worſhip him in your owne perſons. For thus do all his <hi>Saints,</hi> they all ſit downe at his feet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3.</note> that euery one of them may receiue of his <hi>words:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7.</note> euery one of them appeareth before him in <hi>Sion.</hi> Come, and offer to him the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth: ſo did the <hi>godly</hi> vnder the <hi>Law;</hi> ſo doe you vnder the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> worſhip him right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: then they gaue him the burnt <hi>offerings</hi> of fat <hi>Rams, Bulls,</hi> and <hi>Goats:</hi> now giue him that which is your reaſonable <hi>ſeruice</hi> of him; euen in all thankfulneſſe for all his <hi>mercies</hi> towards you in Chriſt <hi>Ieſus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> preſent your bodies a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>ſacrifice, holy,</hi> and <hi>acceptable</hi> to him. Come, &amp; <hi>worſhip</hi> him delightfully, <hi>pray,</hi> giue him thankes, <hi>heare</hi> his <hi>Word,</hi> receiue his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> with holy <hi>incenſe,</hi> with a <hi>pure</hi> mind,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8.</note>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150664:29"/>with <hi>truth</hi> in the inward affections,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28 <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17.</note> with <hi>grace</hi> in your <hi>hearts,</hi> and in the <hi>Name</hi> of the Lord <hi>Ieſus.</hi> For this hee <hi>loueth;</hi> this is pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; in this hee <hi>delighteth;</hi> this makes our <hi>ſacrifices</hi> acceptable vnto him. Come, and <hi>worſhip</hi> him plenteouſly: as they prepared many <hi>Rams,</hi> and <hi>Bulls,</hi> and <hi>Goats</hi> to offer vnto him; ſo prepare to bring in your prayers, plentifull <hi>deuotion;</hi> in your thankeſgiuings, plentifull <hi>affection;</hi> in your hearing his <hi>Word,</hi> plentifull attention; in receiuing his <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> plentifull feeling; and in dedicating your whole <hi>life,</hi> and ſelfe vnto him, plentifull and vnwearied application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will pay thee my vowes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.</note> which my lips haue vttered, and my mouth hath ſpoken when I was in trouble,</hi> or <hi>affliction.</hi>] What the godly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>God</hi> in their <hi>debts, ſickeneſſe,</hi> or any other <hi>miſery,</hi> they are carefull to performe in their <hi>wealth, health,</hi> and <hi>libertie.</hi> Oh thou man, or woman that didſt <hi>vow,</hi> and promiſe to <hi>God,</hi> that if hee brought thee out of <hi>debt,</hi> thou wouldeſt neuer bee a vaine <hi>companion,</hi> a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>waſter,</hi> an idle <hi>walker,</hi> vnthriſtie, vngodly any more;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3.</note> but <hi>honour</hi> him with thy <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and extend thy liberalitie to his <hi>Saints!</hi> O, thou that didſt in thy <hi>ſore</hi> ſickeneſſe promiſe and <hi>vow</hi> vnto him, that if hee brought thee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150664:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>to <hi>health</hi> againe, thou wouldeſt neuer neglect the <hi>Church,</hi> neglect <hi>hearing</hi> his <hi>Word,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane his holy <hi>day, ſweare, lye,</hi> keepe ill <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> bee <hi>vnruly</hi> any more; but feare, honour, ſerue him, liue like a good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> all thy life! O, thou that didſt in any kind of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, <hi>trouble,</hi> or miſery promiſe and <hi>vow</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that if hee would deliuer thee, thou wouldeſt neuer be irreligious, <hi>vnholy,</hi> wicked, diſobedient any more; but doe all ſuch <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> obſerue all ſuch <hi>orders,</hi> follow all ſuch <hi>Wayes</hi> as moſt agree to his <hi>holy</hi> will, and <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>glory!</hi> And hath he been kind vnto thee, according to thy <hi>neceſsities?</hi> and haſt not thou paid thy <hi>vowes</hi> vnto him, which thy <hi>lips</hi> vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in thine affliction? but denied, neglected, or forgotten the ſame?</p>
            <p>Oh, how vniuſt, how vnthankefull, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, how diſhoneſt, how ſhamefull is this? So to <hi>promiſe,</hi> was as <hi>little</hi> as thou couldeſt doe; and wilt thou not reſpect to doe ſo <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> that hath done ſo much for thee, as to indeuour to performe thy promiſe? Thou wouldeſt haue giuen any thing, and been at any <hi>coſt</hi> to haue bin deliuered; GOD hath done it freely for thee, and doſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to <hi>pay</hi> him thy <hi>vowed</hi> ſeruice? Whom wilt thou regard?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.11.</note> To whom wilt thou keepe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150664:30"/>thy <hi>word,</hi> ſince thou lieſt vnto <hi>God?</hi> Thou canſt no way excuſe thy ſelfe:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> if thou plead raſhneſſe, and haſte; oh, how durſt thou be raſh and haſtie, to ſpeake thou couldeſt not tell what vnto the high <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Heauen?</hi> If thou confeſſe it was thy <hi>folly;</hi> why, hee hath no pleaſure in <hi>fooles.</hi> If thou thinke it no great matter, thou deceiueſt thy ſelfe, in promiſing without <hi>conſcience</hi> to performe; thy <hi>mouth</hi> hath cauſed thy whole ſelfe to ſtand <hi>guiltie</hi> of much <hi>ſinne:</hi> better it had beene (though that would haue witneſſed thine <hi>vnthankfulneſſe,</hi> and forgetting of <hi>God</hi>) that thou hadſt not <hi>vowed,</hi> then to vow, and not to <hi>pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, Chriſtian, doe thou both, <hi>vow,</hi> and <hi>pay:</hi> God by troubles and afflictions doth (as it were) call thee, and euen importune thee to vow ſometing vnto him; as ſome lawfull, allowed &amp; preſcribed <hi>teſtimony</hi> of thy thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: if thy <hi>lips</hi> haue vttered, and thy <hi>mouth</hi> hath aduiſedly, reuerently, and <hi>holily</hi> ſpoken ſome <hi>vow</hi> vnto his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> in the <hi>day</hi> of thy miſerie; ſee that thou carefully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, as ſoone as hee grants thee any <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery.</hi> If a filthy fornicatour, and a rebellious fornicatreſſe, pretend <hi>conſcience</hi> of keeping their abominable <hi>vow</hi> againſt all GODS forbid;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 11.3.</note> if <hi>Micha's</hi> mother, making a mad
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150664:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>vow</hi> to make a grauen <hi>image</hi> for her ſonne, was ſo diligent to performe it; oh, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhould wee be to <hi>pay</hi> our lawfull and holy <hi>vowes,</hi> a part of his <hi>worſhip</hi> vnto GOD? Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, praiſe, peace, patterne, and profit requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this at vs. <hi>Precept</hi> of GOD; for hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth vs to <hi>pay</hi> our <hi>vowes</hi> vnto him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.4.</note> and that <hi>quickly,</hi> without delay. <hi>Praiſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.1.</note> for this is a part of the <hi>praiſe</hi> giuen to <hi>Sion,</hi> that in it the <hi>vow</hi> ſhall be performed vnto GOD. <hi>Peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 23.21</note> for if we haue ſpeedily <hi>paid</hi> that wee <hi>vowed,</hi> our conſcience ſhall excuſe vs of that inquiry, and that ſinne, that otherwiſe wee are guiltie of. <hi>Patterne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20</note> for this is exemplified to vs in <hi>Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kob;</hi> in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> in <hi>Dauid;</hi> in <hi>Hannah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 21.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.</note> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>holy</hi> ones: and paying our <hi>vowes</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> wee follow their godly <hi>example. Profit;</hi> for if wee <hi>pay</hi> our <hi>vowes</hi> to GOD,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11</note> hee will ſtill giue vs more <hi>bleſsings,</hi> and make vs haue ſuch experience of his <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> as each one of vs ſhall haue cauſe to ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come, and heare, all yee that feare God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 16.</note> and I will tell you what hee hath done for my ſoule.</hi>] The knowledge of <hi>Gods</hi> goodneſſe to his <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in generall, moueth the true <hi>godly</hi> to note what it is to themſelues in particular. Oh, beware heere of the moſt fearefull <hi>ſpirit</hi> of ſome; I meane of the ſpitefull wicked: for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150664:31"/>when they ſee GODS goodneſſe to his <hi>people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 112.10.</note> they be grieued at it, they <hi>gnaſh</hi> their <hi>teeth</hi> for <hi>anger,</hi> and they <hi>melt</hi> away with <hi>enuy:</hi> which ſheweth that they are inſpired with the <hi>malice</hi> of the <hi>Deuill:</hi> for from the beginning, he and his haue beene ſo helliſhly-minded. But <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> and take your marke by it: the true <hi>godly</hi> put the ſight, and <hi>knowledge</hi> of this to a moſt worthy and excellent vſe: for it moueth them to note, what Gods goodnes is to their very <hi>ſelues</hi> in their owne particular.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> doe thou ſo: haſt thou <hi>heard</hi> what great, <hi>excellent,</hi> wonderfull, and what comfortable things, God in all <hi>ages</hi> hath done for his <hi>people,</hi> to witneſſe his <hi>mercy, loue, righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> vnto them, and to make them <hi>hope</hi> in him, <hi>truſt</hi> in his <hi>Name,</hi> ſerue him, and be aſſured that they are <hi>bleſſed</hi> of him? Oh thinke, and obſerue what he hath <hi>done</hi> alſo for thy <hi>perſon!</hi> Oh, if thou canſt <hi>tell</hi> of none, but common to euery <hi>creature,</hi> yea and to the <hi>vniuſt,</hi> as well as to the <hi>iuſt,</hi> then thy <hi>caſe</hi> is vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable: but if thou find, that to thee alſo hee doth <hi>communicate</hi> his ſpeciall kindneſſe, and his ſingular <hi>fauour;</hi> then thou haſt that which is for <hi>comfort,</hi> for reioycing, for <hi>aſſurance,</hi> and for <hi>inſtruction:</hi> for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, becauſe thereby thou ſeeſt that <hi>God</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150664:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>thee, as <hi>one</hi> of his owne, by doing for thee, as for his very <hi>owne.</hi> For reioycing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereby <hi>God</hi> giues thee reaſon to ſing with bleſſed <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46.</note> My <hi>ſoule</hi> doth <hi>magnifie</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> and my ſpirit <hi>reioyceth</hi> in <hi>God</hi> my <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> for he hath done <hi>great</hi> things for me. For <hi>aſſurance,</hi> becauſe thereby thou art aſſured, that <hi>God</hi> remembreth thee with the <hi>fauour</hi> of his owne <hi>people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.4, 5.</note> and makes thee ſee the <hi>feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie</hi> of his <hi>choſen.</hi> For <hi>inſtruction,</hi> becauſe thereby thou art fitted to relate the <hi>goodneſse</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> vnto others out of thy owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come, and heare, and I will tell you, what God hath done for my ſoule.</hi>] Hee that is guided by a right <hi>ſpirit,</hi> is carefull to vſe all <hi>good</hi> meanes to bring <hi>others</hi> comfort. Oh, the ſcarefull car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of ſuch as bee guided by a froward, and vncleane <hi>ſpirit,</hi> as <hi>Cain, Saul, Doeg, Iudas,</hi> and the like: for theſe vſe what <hi>meanes</hi> they can to bring to others, and eſpecially to the <hi>godly,</hi> diſcomfort. Oh, <hi>happy</hi> are they that are gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a right <hi>ſpirit:</hi> for they ſeeke euery <hi>way</hi> to comfort others, chiefly ſuch as are <hi>godly:</hi> they lead a <hi>life</hi> to comfort them, performe good <hi>actions</hi> to comfort them, and they lay vp <hi>words</hi> to comfort them: they euen pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to relate what <hi>ſweetnes</hi> they haue found
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150664:32"/>in <hi>Gods</hi> goodneſſe towards their owne <hi>ſoules,</hi> vnto other <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to reioyce, and <hi>ſolace</hi> their <hi>holy mindes</hi> therewith:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.26, 27.</note> ſo did <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Antioch:</hi> ſo did <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to the Chriſtians in the houſe of <hi>Mary</hi> praying together:
<note place="margin">12.12, 17.</note> teaching vs the like <hi>zeale, delight, loue,</hi> and <hi>deſire</hi> to comfort <hi>others, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſtands forth and ſaith to the godly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come, and heare, all yee that feare God.</hi>] It is a Chriſtians <hi>dutie</hi> to heare of <hi>Gods</hi> priuate and ſpeciall <hi>benignitie.</hi> O worldling, thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureſt nothing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.7.</note> but this tranſitory <hi>world:</hi> O profane perſon,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 18.15.</note> thou holdeſt ſuch <hi>queſtions,</hi> nothing but <hi>vaine</hi> words, and <hi>idle</hi> names: O hypocrite, thou (meaſuring another by thy line) accounteſt ſuch relation, but vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: O ſincere Chriſtian, it is my <hi>dutie</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12, 14.</note> and thine to <hi>heare</hi> it; for thou feareſt <hi>God,</hi> and ſo oughteſt to haue the <hi>ſpeciall</hi> things of <hi>God</hi> reuealed vnto thee: thou feareſt <hi>God,</hi> and ſo wilt bee glad to <hi>heare</hi> how kind <hi>God</hi> hath beene vnto me:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.74.</note> thou feareſt <hi>God,</hi> and ſo wilt cheere thine owne <hi>ſoule</hi> with that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which thou heareſt that <hi>God</hi> hath giuen to anothers <hi>ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I will declare what hee hath done for my ſoule.</hi>] It agreeth to true <hi>pietie,</hi> to declare our owne experience of <hi>Gods</hi> ſpeciall <hi>mercy.</hi> O
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150664:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>man, or woman, to whom <hi>God</hi> hath beene ſpecially mercifull,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 106.7, 21.</note> and thou haſt not <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood</hi> it: O thou to whom he hath vouchſafed a <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>mercies,</hi> and thou haſt not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred</hi> them: O thou, for whom hee hath done <hi>great</hi> things, and thou haſt forgotten him: O thou,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.</note> with whom he hath <hi>dealt</hi> more graciouſly, then with many <hi>others,</hi> and thou doeſt not ſo much as thinke, or ſpeake of it: O thou,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</note> whom he hath <hi>crowned</hi> with rare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignities, and thou haſt lightly <hi>eſteemed</hi> both himſelfe, and his benefits: how peruerſe, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and impious is this thy <hi>dealing?</hi> Many would faine ſee that, which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>offered</hi> thee to ſee, and cannot: many would faine <hi>heare</hi> that, which thou mighteſt <hi>heare,</hi> and may not: many would turne vnto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>loue</hi> him, and <hi>praiſe</hi> him, if thoſe <hi>glorious</hi> things, mighty <hi>workes,</hi> and gracious <hi>doctrines</hi> were vttered to them, that haue beene plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully ſhewed vnto thee: <hi>woe</hi> vnto thee for thine ingratitude, <hi>woe</hi> vnto thee for thine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Chriſtian,</hi> be it otherwiſe with thee;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 40.10.</note> ſhew thy <hi>pietie,</hi> by declaring thine owne <hi>experience</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> ſpeciall <hi>mercy,</hi> as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did: as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did: as <hi>Hannah</hi> did: as <hi>Mary</hi> did: as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> did: hide not his <hi>righteouſneſse</hi> within
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150664:33"/>thine <hi>heart:</hi> conceale not his louing kindnes, but <hi>declare</hi> his <hi>mercy,</hi> and his <hi>ſaluation.</hi> Thou declareſt to thy <hi>wife,</hi> or to thy <hi>neighbour,</hi> thy <hi>experience</hi> of ſome <hi>friends</hi> ſpeciall friendly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; O how much <hi>more</hi> ſhouldeſt thou, to winne them to God alſo, declare to <hi>wife,</hi> and <hi>family,</hi> and neighbours, thine <hi>experience</hi> of Gods ſpeciall <hi>mercy?</hi> Imitate this <hi>holy</hi> man, ſaying: Come, let your <hi>worke</hi> alone a little <hi>while;</hi> come, let your buſineſſe ſtay a little <hi>while;</hi> come, leaue off your other communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation a little <hi>while;</hi> come, ſit downe by me, and giue eare a <hi>while</hi> to what I ſhall <hi>tell</hi> you, and <hi>heare,</hi> and I will tell you <hi>excellent,</hi> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, comfortable things, euen</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What God, hath done for my ſoule.</hi>] Much of our bounden <hi>praiſe</hi> of God, conſiſts in an <hi>holy</hi> obſeruation, and faithfull mention of our owne part, in the particular <hi>goodneſse</hi> of God. O thou, whom God doth not afford the matter of ſuch obſeruation: O thou, to whom God giues no cauſe of any ſuch men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17.</note> but lets thee alone, like <hi>Ephraim,</hi> like thoſe <hi>blind</hi> leaders: leaues thee in fearefull <hi>hunger,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14</note> thirſt, ſhame,</hi> ſorrow of <hi>heart,</hi> and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.</note> like thoſe that forſake him: <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers</hi> thee to walke in thine owne wayes, like all the <hi>Heathen</hi> of old time:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.16</note> giues thee vp
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150664:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto <hi>vile</hi> affections, and to a <hi>reprobate</hi> mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26, 28.</note> like thoſe vnreaſonable <hi>Idolaters:</hi> thou canſt not ſing of his <hi>Name,</hi> thou canſt not <hi>praiſe</hi> him, thou canſt not <hi>glorifie</hi> him; but cleane contrary. And this is the <hi>puniſhment,</hi> the <hi>plague,</hi> the iudgement of God, that thou canſt be <hi>merrie,</hi> but not in him: thou canſt <hi>reioyce,</hi> but not in him: thou canſt ſhew <hi>teſtimonies</hi> of his <hi>wrath</hi> againſt thy <hi>ſoule,</hi> but thou canſt not tell of any <hi>grace</hi> hee hath giuen to thy <hi>ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O happy <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> remember wherein thy bounden <hi>thankes</hi> to God, and the plentifull argument of thy <hi>praiſing</hi> of him conſiſteth, namely, in thy <hi>holy</hi> obſeruation, and faithfull mention of thy owne part in his particular <hi>goodneſse.</hi> O how great is his goodneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 31.19.</note> that hee hath <hi>laid</hi> vp for them that <hi>feare</hi> him! Be thou wiſe to obſerue thy part in it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.42.</note> that thou maiſt vnderſtand the <hi>Lords</hi> louing kindneſſe vnto thy <hi>ſoule:</hi> obſerue whether thou canſt ſay with the <hi>Prophet;</hi> Come and <hi>heare,</hi> all you that feare God, and I will <hi>tell</hi> you what hee hath <hi>done</hi> for my <hi>ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee hath <hi>choſen</hi> mee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.3.</note> and ſet mee apart for himſelfe: In the <hi>Volume</hi> of his <hi>Booke</hi> of Life,
<note place="margin">40.7.</note> my <hi>Name</hi> is written in <hi>Heauen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">23.3. 31.7.</note> Hee hath <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted,</hi> and reſtored my <hi>ſoule:</hi> He hath <hi>knowne</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:150664:34"/>my <hi>ſoule</hi> in aduerſitie:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.3.</note> Hee hath brought my ſoule from the <hi>graue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">86.13.</note> He hath deliuered my <hi>ſoule</hi> from the loweſt <hi>hell:</hi>
               <note place="margin">71.17.</note> Hee himſelfe hath <hi>taught</hi> me,
<note place="margin">32.5.</note> euen from my <hi>youth:</hi> He hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen mine <hi>iniquitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">103.10, 13</note> and my <hi>ſinne:</hi> Hee hath not <hi>dealt</hi> with me after my <hi>ſinnes,</hi> nor rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mee according to mine <hi>iniquities:</hi> As a <hi>father</hi> pittieth his <hi>children,</hi> ſo hee hath <hi>pittied</hi> me:
<note place="margin">118.6, 7, 21.</note> He is on my <hi>ſide,</hi> he taketh my <hi>part:</hi> He is become my <hi>ſaluation:</hi> Hee vpholdeth mee in mine <hi>integritie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">41.12.</note> I was brought <hi>low,</hi> and hee <hi>helped</hi> me:
<note place="margin">116.6.</note> Sometime hee hath ſhewed mee <hi>great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">71.20.</note> and ſore <hi>troubles;</hi> but hee hath by and by <hi>quickned</hi> me againe: He hath brought me <hi>vp</hi> againe out of my <hi>deepe</hi> miſeries: He hath <hi>increaſed</hi> mine <hi>honour:</hi> Hee hath returned to <hi>comfort</hi> me on euery <hi>ſide:</hi> Hee hath <hi>healed</hi> all my <hi>diſeaſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">103.3.</note> He hath deliuered my <hi>ſoule</hi> from <hi>death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">116.8.</note> mine <hi>eyes</hi> from <hi>teares,</hi> and my <hi>feet</hi> from falling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cryed vnto him with my mouth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 17.</note> and I was exalted for the words of my tongue.</hi>] I cryed earneſtly vnto him in my grieuous <hi>miſery,</hi> and becauſe I <hi>prayed</hi> without doubting, in a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt <hi>faith,</hi> he lifted me <hi>vp</hi> out of all my <hi>feares:</hi> Hee hath <hi>deliuered</hi> mee,
<note place="margin">71.3.</note> and cauſed mee to <hi>eſcape:</hi> Hee hath giuen commandement to <hi>ſaue</hi> me:
<note place="margin">139.17, 18</note> O how <hi>precious</hi> are his <hi>thoughts</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150664:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>mee! how <hi>great</hi> is the <hi>ſumme</hi> of them! If I ſhould <hi>count</hi> them, they are <hi>moe</hi> in number then the <hi>ſand:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 116.7, 23, 6.</note> Hee hath dealt ſo bountifully with mee, as ſurely <hi>goodneſse,</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> ſhall <hi>follow</hi> me all the <hi>dayes</hi> of my <hi>life,</hi> and I ſhall euen <hi>dwell</hi> in his <hi>Houſe</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>Canſt thou tell all this the <hi>Lords</hi> admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doing to thy <hi>ſoule</hi> (as euery experienced <hi>Chriſtian</hi> can?) ſee thou <hi>declare</hi> it, to ſhewthine abundant <hi>reioycing</hi> in God: to <hi>magnifie</hi> his benignitie: to <hi>glorifie</hi> his <hi>Name:</hi> and that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, conſcionably, reuerently; and as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did, which was both (as Gods Saints vſe) to vtter forth abundantly the mention of Gods great goodnes:
<note place="margin">145.7.</note> and alſo to ſhew (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>carnall</hi> mens thoughts) how rich God is to all that <hi>call</hi> vpon him, ſets his <hi>heart</hi> vpon them, <hi>careth</hi> for them, and preferreth them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I regard iniquitie in mine heart,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 18.</note> the Lord will not heare me.</hi>] The <hi>godly</hi> apply that vnto themſelues, if they become like the wicked, which God ſpeaketh properly of them that be wicked. Oh, the <hi>vnbeleefe</hi> of wicked <hi>ones</hi> indeed! for theſe will not <hi>beleeue</hi> the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that properly are threatned againſt them: they <hi>perſwade</hi> themſelues,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.12, 13</note> that no <hi>euill</hi> ſhall come vpon them; they be <hi>conceited</hi> that they ſhal neuer ſee the iudgements <hi>denounced;</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:150664:35"/>they hold the Preachers Words, propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame to be an empty winde: Yea that the Preachers themſelues ſhall ſooner ſmart then they: they bleſſe themſelues in their owne minds; they ſay in their owne thoughts, We ſhall haue <hi>peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 29.19</note> though we walke in the <hi>imagination</hi> of our owne hearts. O intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>blindneſſe!</hi> O high <hi>preſumption!</hi> Hence they adde <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> to their <hi>thirſt;</hi> runne with the <hi>Thiefe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.18 19, 20, 21. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.8.</note> partake with the <hi>adulterer;</hi> haue <hi>hearts</hi> ſet on them to do euill; do neuer think &amp; ſay in themſelues vpon the hearing or ſight how God plagues ſuch as they are, Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely if I be ſtill ſuch a one, God will plague me alſo in the end, and more and more har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their hearts. O the fearefull <hi>effects</hi> of the wicked and vnbeleeuers of that which GOD hath ſet downe as their doome; and yet this is not neere all:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.15. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Deu.</hi> 23.20.</note> for hence they fall into more euill, they doe euen belye God himſelfe, and God denies them his <hi>mercy,</hi> beſides, hence they cannot repent.</p>
            <p>But the true godly beleeueth and applyeth to himſelfe, if he do that which is wicked, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſame <hi>puniſhment</hi> which God himſelfe ſpeaketh <hi>properly</hi> to them that are wicked: he expects no other, he lookes for no <hi>toleration,</hi> hee hopes for no <hi>diſpenſation:</hi> he ſaith with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150664:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Iob,</hi> If I <hi>ſin</hi> with the <hi>vaine</hi> perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 3.1.</note> or the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers,</hi> or the <hi>adulterers,</hi> or the <hi>cruell</hi> Maſters, or the <hi>oppreſſours,</hi> or the <hi>vncharitables,</hi> or the <hi>vniuſts,</hi> or the <hi>idolatrous</hi> couetous ones, or the <hi>vngodly</hi> worldlings, or the ſpitefull <hi>euious</hi> ones, or the churliſh <hi>Nabals,</hi> or the common <hi>ſorts</hi> ſinne, or any <hi>ſinne;</hi> the <hi>plagues</hi> of ſuch <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> will come <hi>vpon</hi> me. Hee ſaith with the <hi>Church,</hi> If I <hi>deale</hi> falſly in <hi>Gods Couenant;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17, 18, 20, 21.</note> if I turne backe, if I <hi>forget</hi> his <hi>Name,</hi> if I lift vp my <hi>hands</hi> to a ſtrange <hi>god,</hi> he hath ſaid, He wil <hi>ſearch</hi> out ſuch <hi>ſinners</hi> to puniſh them, and therefore I ſhall not <hi>eſcape,</hi> but hee will ſurely <hi>ſearch</hi> mee, and my <hi>ſinne</hi> out alſo. Hee ſaith with <hi>Dauid,</hi> God hath <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15.</note> When the <hi>wicked</hi> doe <hi>ſpread</hi> forth their hands, I will <hi>hide</hi> mine <hi>eyes</hi> from them; when they make many <hi>prayers,</hi> I will not <hi>heare</hi> them.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.</note> I doe not <hi>heare</hi> ſinning ſinners; therefore, If I <hi>regard</hi> wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in mine <hi>heart,</hi> I <hi>beleeue</hi> that I ſhall <hi>fare</hi> alike; out of all doubt he will not <hi>heare</hi> me.</p>
            <p>Thus the truely <hi>godly</hi> apply Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to themſelues; and that, becauſe of their <hi>beleefe,</hi> and their experience; they <hi>belecue</hi> that he is ſo <hi>true,</hi> as hee will not breake any of his <hi>words;</hi> they <hi>beleeue</hi> that he is ſo <hi>holy,</hi> as he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>indure</hi> any to haue <hi>acceſse</hi> vnto him in their ſins; they <hi>beleeue</hi> he is ſo <hi>iuſt,</hi> as he iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150664:36"/>without <hi>reſpect</hi> of perſon;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 22.20.</note> they obſerue in their owne experience, how, as God hath threatned, euen ſo hee hath <hi>executed</hi> vpon them that haue <hi>ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh the <hi>happy,</hi> and bleſſed fruits of the <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies beliefe</hi> of Gods iudgement, euen vpon themſelues, if they <hi>fall</hi> vnto ſin! Hence they <hi>ſtay</hi> themſelues from yeelding to <hi>temptations,</hi> ſaying:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9.</note> How can I doe this <hi>great</hi> wickednes, and ſo ſin againſt God? Hence, though they <hi>indure</hi> neuer ſo much <hi>affliction,</hi> yet they <hi>hold</hi> faithfull,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17.</note> ſaying: All this is come vpon vs, yet haue we not forgotten thee. Hence they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to <hi>preuent</hi> ſin in their brethren, leſt they bee iudged together with them, ſaying, to thoſe that they thinke are <hi>reuolting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieſh.</hi> 22.17.</note> Is the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of <hi>Peor</hi> too <hi>little</hi> for vs, from which we are not <hi>clenſed</hi> vntill this <hi>day;</hi> but that yee muſt turne <hi>away</hi> from God, and ſo you <hi>rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to day, to morrow his <hi>wrath</hi> will come vpon vs all? ſaying, to them that <hi>breake</hi> the <hi>Sabbath;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.17, 18.</note> What <hi>euill</hi> thing is this that ye do? Did not your <hi>Fathers</hi> thus, and did not God bring all this <hi>euill</hi> vpon vs, and vpon this <hi>City?</hi> Yet ye bring more <hi>wrath</hi> vpon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Hence they liue alwaies in <hi>feare</hi> to offend,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> ſaying, Since wee <hi>call</hi> him <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that <hi>iudgeth</hi> without reſpect of <hi>perſon,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150664:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>cording to euery <hi>man;</hi> worke, let vs paſſe the <hi>time</hi> of our <hi>ſoiourning</hi> heere in <hi>feare.</hi> Hence the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, I will <hi>waſh</hi> mine <hi>hands</hi> in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and ſo compaſſe <hi>Gods Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord will not heare mee.</hi>] They are in wofull miſery, whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> regard <hi>iniquitie.</hi> O man, or woman, whoſe <hi>heart</hi> imagineth that which is <hi>euill:</hi> becauſe thou art in <hi>health,</hi> in <hi>peace,</hi> in <hi>wealth,</hi> in <hi>proſperity,</hi> at <hi>hearts-eaſe;</hi> doeſt thou thinke that thou art not in <hi>miſery?</hi> Yes, yes, thou art in <hi>wofull</hi> miſery. For becauſe thine <hi>heart</hi> deuiſeth, <hi>nouriſheth,</hi> and regardeth <hi>iniquitie,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> doth not <hi>heare</hi> thee: this is thy <hi>miſerie,</hi> and this is a grieuous <hi>miſery;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</note> This was the miſery of <hi>Cain,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> would not <hi>heare</hi> him. This is the miſery of ſuch as <hi>heare</hi> not <hi>Gods</hi> Word to <hi>obey</hi> it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.9.</note> that <hi>God</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not their <hi>prayer,</hi> but holdeth it <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.11, 12.</note> this is the <hi>miſery</hi> of ſuch as fall <hi>away</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> that he will neither <hi>heare</hi> their owne <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> nor haue his <hi>Prophets pray</hi> for them; this is the <hi>miſery</hi> of ſuch as refuſe to bee <hi>reclaimed</hi> from their <hi>old cuſtomes,</hi> vanities, and <hi>ſollies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.28.</note> that though they come in their extremities, and <hi>call</hi> earneſtly, and ſeeke <hi>early</hi> vnto God for <hi>mercy,</hi> hee will not be <hi>found</hi> of them, hee will not <hi>anſwer</hi> them, he will not <hi>heare</hi> them; this is the <hi>miſery</hi> of ſuch, as for all Gods continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150664:37"/>
               <hi>paines,</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> and <hi>coſt</hi> in bringing them <hi>vp</hi> like <hi>children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> yet they <hi>rebell</hi> againſt him; that hee <hi>delighteth</hi> not in their <hi>ſacrifices;</hi> that hee is <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with their <hi>appearing</hi> before him, that he <hi>accounteth</hi> their <hi>offerings</hi> and their <hi>incenſe</hi> abomination; that hee cannot <hi>away</hi> with their <hi>holy</hi> dayes, their <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> their <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne</hi> meetings; that hee <hi>hateth</hi> their high times, takes them a <hi>trouble</hi> to him, is <hi>weary</hi> of them, cannot <hi>beare</hi> them, and that hee <hi>hideth</hi> his <hi>eyes</hi> from them, and will not <hi>heare</hi> their <hi>prayers.</hi> Oh conſider this, thou, whoſe <hi>heart</hi> is full of wickednes, whoſe <hi>heart</hi> regardeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>pietie,</hi> truth, or <hi>mercy,</hi> but iniquitie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, <hi>vanitie:</hi> conſider and ſee, if this be not a ſure, and heauy <hi>miſery,</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> will not <hi>heare</hi> thee.</p>
            <p>O beleeue, as thou oughteſt, that it is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous <hi>miſery</hi> indeed: for what is a more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous <hi>miſery,</hi> then Gods moſt ſeuere <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> and as the foreſaid places doe <hi>proue,</hi> it is one of his threatned <hi>fearefull</hi> iudgements; ſuch a <hi>iudgement,</hi> as makes the godly <hi>lament,</hi> ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.8.</note> When I <hi>cry,</hi> and ſhout, hee ſhutteth out my <hi>prayer:</hi> ſuch a <hi>iudgement,</hi> as make vs vnto our ſelues <hi>comfortleſſe.</hi> For what comfort can we haue, when we cannot haue <hi>comfort</hi> in God? And what comfort can we haue in <hi>him,</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150664:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>while he <hi>will</hi> not <hi>heare</hi> vs? Such a <hi>iudgement,</hi> as makes vs vnto others <hi>helpeleſse:</hi> for what <hi>helpe</hi> can we giue them, when we can <hi>procure</hi> no <hi>helpe</hi> to them from God? And how can we procure <hi>helpe</hi> to them from <hi>him,</hi> when he wil not <hi>heare</hi> vs? ſuch a <hi>iudgement,</hi> as <hi>denies</hi> vs <hi>hope</hi> of all benefits for <hi>body,</hi> and <hi>ſoule:</hi> for what <hi>hope</hi> can wee haue to obtaine any of them, when <hi>God,</hi> at whom wee <hi>ſeeke</hi> them, and of whom <hi>alone</hi> wee muſt <hi>receiue</hi> them, will not heare vs? Such a iudgement, as preſages to vs <hi>finall</hi> excluſion: for what can we <hi>looke</hi> for, but that in the end <hi>God</hi> will ſay to vs, <hi>Away</hi> from me yee <hi>workers</hi> of iniquitie?</p>
            <p>But, <hi>bleſſed</hi> Chriſtian,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12</note> that haſt ſo caſt off the <hi>workes</hi> of darkneſſe: <hi>waſhed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 1.16.</note> and made <hi>cleane</hi> thy ſelfe: put <hi>away</hi> the <hi>euill</hi> of thy <hi>works</hi> out of <hi>Gods</hi> ſight: ceaſed to doe <hi>euill:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.13.</note> clenſed</hi> thine <hi>heart</hi> from the wickedneſſe, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie thereof: abandoned the <hi>loue</hi> of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: thou <hi>eſcapeſt</hi> this <hi>wofull</hi> miſery, and thou partakeſt his moſt comfortable <hi>mercy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.31.</note> for be <hi>heareth</hi> thy <hi>prayers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.24.</note> euen while thou art <hi>ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> he will <hi>heare,</hi> and before thou <hi>calleſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.8.</note> he will <hi>anſwer;</hi> yea, thy <hi>prayer</hi> is his <hi>delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O here is a <hi>mercy</hi> indeed: ſuch a <hi>mercy,</hi> as <hi>intitles</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe with that <hi>honourable</hi> deſcription; O thou that heareſt <hi>Sions</hi> prayer:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2.</note>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150664:38"/>ſuch a <hi>mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8.30, 32, 34.36, 39, 43, 45, 49.</note> as in the <hi>dedication</hi> of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> King <hi>Salomon</hi> chiefly prayed for ſaying, to euery kind of <hi>occaſion</hi> of <hi>prayer;</hi> Then <hi>heare</hi> thou in Heauen thy dwelling <hi>place:</hi> Such a <hi>mercy,</hi> as makes vs able to <hi>comfort</hi> our ſelues in <hi>God</hi> in all our neceſſities: ſuch a <hi>mercy,</hi> as armes vs againſt diſcomfort in all <hi>miſeries:</hi> ſuch a <hi>mercy,</hi> as makes vs <hi>hopefull</hi> of all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and <hi>eternall</hi> bleſſings.</p>
            <p>For whom he <hi>promiſeth</hi> ſo to <hi>heare,</hi> he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the <hi>purpoſe</hi> indeed:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.17.</note> as it is ſaid, The <hi>righteous cry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">145.19.</note> and the <hi>Lord</hi> heareth, &amp; deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them out of all their <hi>troubles.</hi> They that <hi>feare</hi> him, <hi>cry,</hi> and he <hi>heareth</hi> their cry, and <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi> them. They <hi>aske,</hi> and he granteth: they <hi>ſeeke,</hi> and hee lets them find: they <hi>knocke,</hi> and he opens vnto them: they <hi>pray,</hi> and hee giues them good things: they <hi>deſire,</hi> and hee giues them the <hi>Holy</hi> Ghoſt. This <hi>mercy</hi> is moſt worthy to be noted; this <hi>fauour</hi> is moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be obſerued; this <hi>bleſsing</hi> the holy <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> tooke ſuch notice of, as hee was <hi>able</hi> to ſay:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>But verily God hath heard me, he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended vnto the voyce of my prayer.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Oh,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2.116.1.4.3.6.8, 9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.8.</note> this <hi>moues</hi> them to come vnto him <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly:</hi> this <hi>moues</hi> them to loue him <hi>dearely:</hi> this <hi>aſſureth</hi> them, that hee highly regardeth them: this <hi>comforteth</hi> them againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150664:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>this cauſeth others to <hi>honour</hi> them,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.31.</note> with crauing their <hi>prayers:</hi> this <hi>witneſſeth</hi> that they <hi>obey</hi> his <hi>Word,</hi> that they worſhip him,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.22.5.14.</note> that they doe his <hi>will,</hi> that they doe the <hi>things</hi> which pleaſe him: that they pray according to his <hi>will:</hi> that the <hi>Spirit</hi> prayeth in, and for them.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27.</note> This makes them the moſtprofit able <hi>members</hi> in a family, in a towne, in a city, in a kingdom: this proues to themſelues, and others, their integrity, and vpright <hi>heart</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and that (notwithſtanding, through humane <hi>frailtie</hi> they erre in many things) they cheriſh no <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> they diſgeſt no wickedneſſe, they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no <hi>euill</hi> in their <hi>hearts.</hi> This ſpeciall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit <hi>Dauid</hi> got, by obſeruing how <hi>God</hi> heard his <hi>prayers,</hi> and thence reaſoned, ſaying, If I regard <hi>iniquitie</hi> in mine <hi>heart,</hi> God will not <hi>heare</hi> me: but verily God hath <hi>heard</hi> me, and attended vnto the <hi>voyce</hi> of my <hi>prayer:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who dare ſay, that I regard any <hi>iniquitie</hi> in my <hi>heart?</hi> Laſtly, this obſeruation prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth (as it ought) the true <hi>godly,</hi> to great <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe;</hi> as it did this holy man, ſaying:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed be God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 20.</note> which hath not put backe my prayer from him; nor his mercy from me.</hi>] Gods not refuſing our prayers, and his not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding his <hi>mercy</hi> from vs, requireth ſpeciall <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> at vs. O they, that haue had
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150664:39"/>much, and long <hi>experience,</hi> how God hath not put backe their prayers, nor kept away his mercy from them; and yet the <hi>time</hi> is to come that they haue made, euen very this <hi>point,</hi> an argument of <hi>thankeſgiuing.</hi> O this, euen this <hi>one</hi> neglected, this <hi>one</hi> vnknowne, this <hi>one</hi> forgotten <hi>dutie,</hi> puts them into the <hi>guilt</hi> of much <hi>iniquitie;</hi> as the <hi>guilt</hi> of preſuming, that God owes them the <hi>hearing</hi> of their <hi>prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and that he <hi>owes</hi> them his <hi>mercy:</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> of eſteeming, that it is no ſuch great <hi>matter,</hi> that he turnes not <hi>away</hi> their prayers from him, or his <hi>mercy</hi> from them: the <hi>guilt</hi> of not reckoning theſe among Gods ſpeciall <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits:</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> of <hi>ignorance,</hi> that theſe are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>ſignes</hi> of his <hi>goodnes,</hi> and do deſerue high <hi>account,</hi> much <hi>praiſe,</hi> and great <hi>thankfulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, O Chriſtian, if this haue beene thy guilt, <hi>repent</hi> vnfainedly thereof; ſhew thy ſelfe <hi>ſorrowfull</hi> before God for it; make <hi>ſuite</hi> to him for the <hi>pardon</hi> heereof: and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that euer ſince thou waſt <hi>called,</hi> thou haſt been a <hi>petitioner</hi> vnto him; remembring, that thou haſt made innumerable <hi>requeſts</hi> to him; remembring, that hee might <hi>iustly</hi> haue excepted againſt thy <hi>petitions,</hi> for diuers <hi>wants</hi> in the beſt of them; remembring, that thou art moſt <hi>vnworthy</hi> to vtter thy mind vnto his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150664:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>moſt high <hi>Maiestie;</hi> remembring, that thou art not <hi>worthy</hi> of the very leaſt of his <hi>daily,</hi> hourely, continuall, <hi>corporall, ſpirituall,</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, more neceſſary, moſt neceſſary <hi>innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercies,</hi> that hee hath ſhewed, doth ſhew, and according to his faithfull <hi>promiſe</hi> will ſhew vnto thee.</p>
            <p>Remember theſe things, and then thinke; how for all thy often comming, thy neuer ceaſing to aske at <hi>him</hi> thy manifold <hi>wants,</hi> thy great vnworthineſſe; yet, though a <hi>father,</hi> a <hi>mother,</hi> a moſt kind <hi>friend</hi> would haue been weary; hee neuer ſhewed himſelfe <hi>troubled, grieued,</hi> or <hi>weary,</hi> neuer put backe thy <hi>prayers,</hi> nor kept backe his ſpeciall <hi>mercy,</hi> his moſt needfull <hi>mercy,</hi> nor his ſauing <hi>mercy</hi> from thee. Thinking, I ſay, how for all thou haſt giuen him ſufficient <hi>occaſion</hi> to prouoke him to doe it, yet hee hath not done it; oh bee <hi>thankfull,</hi> oh be thorowly thankfull!</p>
            <p>For who knoweth not, that if he would, he might haue turned <hi>away</hi> thy <hi>prayers</hi> from him: he might <hi>iuſtly</hi> in <hi>anger,</hi> and <hi>ſore</hi> diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure haue reiected them: he might haue <hi>held</hi> backe his <hi>mercy</hi> from thee? Oh what would become of vs, if the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould refuſe our <hi>prayers,</hi> and turne away his <hi>mercy?</hi> Oh then calamities, fearefull deſolation, dreadfull <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150664:40"/>like a <hi>whirlewind,</hi> and ſore <hi>distreſſe,</hi> and <hi>anguiſh</hi> would come vpon vs, and wee ſhould find none to <hi>helpe</hi> vs, there could bee none able to <hi>comfort</hi> vs, in the bitterneſſe of our <hi>ſoules</hi> wee ſhould <hi>lament,</hi> wee ſhould <hi>cry</hi> out, ſaying: Oh, are not all theſe <hi>griefes, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, troubles,</hi> and <hi>euils</hi> come vpon vs, becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> hath put our <hi>prayers</hi> backe from <hi>him,</hi> and kept his <hi>mercy</hi> backe from vs?</p>
            <p>O conſider theſe things, and let vs be <hi>wiſe;</hi> let vs not ſtill prouoke him to <hi>refuſe</hi> our <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> by refuſing his precepts; let vs not ſtill prouoke him to hold back his <hi>mercies,</hi> by our holding backe our <hi>duties:</hi> O, that our ſecure generation, ſo giuen ouer to manifold <hi>prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> could ſo number their <hi>dayes,</hi> as they might apply their hearts ſpeedily to this <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome!</hi> neuer more need of this <hi>wiſedome:</hi> oh, let vs be yet <hi>wiſer:</hi> let vs make ſure, that God ſhall continue not to turne <hi>away</hi> our <hi>prayers</hi> from him, nor his mercy from vs; and this we doe, namely, if we turne not <hi>away</hi> our <hi>hearing,</hi> and <hi>obedient</hi> hearkening from his Word: if wee <hi>hold</hi> not backe our <hi>obedience,</hi> hee will not <hi>hold</hi> backe his <hi>acceptance:</hi> if wee keepe not back our <hi>duty,</hi> he wil not keepe back his <hi>mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if he keepe not backe our <hi>prayers</hi> from himſelfe, nor his <hi>mercy</hi> from vs; oh, how <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:150664:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>are we! Then we haue <hi>aſſurance</hi> that he <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi> vs; forgiues vs; will deliuer vs, and <hi>ſaue</hi> vs; <hi>heale</hi> our Land of all the miſeries thereof; <hi>teach</hi> vs in the good <hi>way</hi> wherein wee ſhould <hi>walke;</hi> and when wee make <hi>mone</hi> becauſe of <hi>drought,</hi> or <hi>famine,</hi> he will heare the Heauens (as it were) crying for vs, and make the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens heare the Earth gaping after raine for vs, and cauſe the Earth to heare the Corne, and the Wine, &amp; the Oyle, longing to grow forth for vs, and will ſee that theſe ſhall heare vs according to our want and ſeuerall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. <hi>[My prayer from himſelfe, nor his mercy from me.]</hi> God makes a <hi>bleſsed</hi> exchange with his bleſſed <hi>ſeruants.</hi> O man, or woman, that ſayeſt otherwiſe: ô thou that ſayeſt; I haue offered vnto God, and he had no reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 21.15.</note> What profit ſhould we haue to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him? We haue <hi>fasted,</hi> and hee beholds vs not; we haue <hi>humbled</hi> our ſelues, and he takes no knowledge of it; wee find no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change; we thinke, the proud and wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue more fauour then we doe; we account tis but in <hi>vaine</hi> to ſerue him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.13.</note> O fearefull ſtout words againſt God, and moſt falſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</note> except thou be naught, as <hi>Cain</hi> was; except thou be an Hypocrite, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> were;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.</note> except thou be a wicked ſeruant, as <hi>Iudas</hi> was; which, if
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150664:41"/>thou be, thou muſt blame thy ſelfe. Otherwiſe thou ſhalt find his <hi>ſeruice,</hi> an happy ſeruice; thou ſhalt find a great difference betweene the righteous,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17, 18.</note> and the wicked; betweene him that ſerueth God, and him that ſerueth him not; betweene the religious, and the irriligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: thou ſhalt find a <hi>ſeruice,</hi> like the ſeruice of a child to his <hi>deare</hi> and louing father. For as a father with ſuch a child: ſo he makes a <hi>bleſſed</hi> exchange with his bleſſed ſeruants.</p>
            <p>They bring him their <hi>offering,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 115.12. <hi>Prou.</hi> 23. <hi>Matt.</hi> 7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> and he giues them his <hi>holy</hi> acceptation: they giue him their <hi>bodies,</hi> and he giues them his <hi>bleſsings:</hi> they giue him their <hi>hearts,</hi> and hee giues them his Spirit, and his grace: they giue him his <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23</note> and hee giues them the comfort of his <hi>ſaluation:</hi> they honor him with their <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and he fils their <hi>barnes</hi> with abundance:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.41, 42. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> they giue his Meſſengers a ſmall reward, and hee giues them a great reward: they draw neere to him, and hee drawes neere to them: they <hi>loue</hi> him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.14, 15. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16, 17.</note> and hee makes all <hi>worke</hi> for the beſt vnto them: they honour him, and he honours them: they thinke of his <hi>Name,</hi> and he keeps in remembrance their <hi>name.</hi> His <hi>glory,</hi> is their <hi>iewel,</hi> and he makes them his <hi>iewels:</hi> they are euer ſending vp their prayers, and praiſes to him, and hee is euer multiplying his <hi>mercies</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150664:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto them: oh, what a <hi>bleſsed</hi> exchange doth he make with his <hi>bleſsed</hi> ſeruants?</p>
            <p>O wonderfull <hi>bounty!</hi> ô admirable <hi>benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!</hi> behold, and admire this <hi>bleſsed</hi> exchange: it is worthy to be <hi>admired</hi> and magnified for euer. For what is it, for which <hi>God</hi> makes this exchange with his <hi>ſeruants?</hi> Oh it is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6.</note> as out of them, and as it is theirs, euen no better then as <hi>filthy</hi> rags: and what are they with whom hee makes it? oh,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6.</note> as of themſelues they are moſt vnworthy; they are euen as an vncleane thing: and what is that, that they giue him, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in it ſelfe? Oh, it is none of theirs,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note> it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what he hath firſt giuen them; it is nothing, but what they haue firſt <hi>receiued</hi> of him; it is only his very owne: they muſt needs <hi>confeſſe,</hi> ſaying, What are we, <hi>O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.14, 16.</note> that we ſhould be able, or apt to <hi>offer</hi> any thing vnto thee? for all things come of thy ſelfe, and of thine own haue we giuen vnto thee: all duties that we render vnto thee, are firſt <hi>taught</hi> vs by thine own <hi>hand,</hi> and all that thou exchangeſt with vs, is thine owne, it is all thine owne.</p>
            <p>O Chriſtian, let this <hi>bleſsed</hi> exchange moue thee to bee euer in an <hi>holy</hi> exchanging with the <hi>Lord:</hi> moue thee to <hi>glory</hi> in his liberality: moue thee to <hi>hold</hi> no gaine comparable to <hi>godlineſse:</hi> moue thee to ſerue the <hi>Lord</hi> with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150664:42"/>gladneſſe: mooue thee to come before him with reioycing: mooue thee to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the <hi>face</hi> of all blaſphemers, that no <hi>ſeruice</hi> is ſo commodious to them that <hi>ſerue</hi> in it, as the <hi>Lords</hi> ſeruice is to his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants;</hi> none ſo <hi>honourable,</hi> none ſo comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and that he is moſt <hi>rich</hi> to all that <hi>call</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: moue thee to <hi>confeſse,</hi> and ſay to him for all his exchanges in <hi>generall;</hi> Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.13.</note> ô my <hi>God,</hi> I thanke thee, and <hi>praiſe</hi> thy glorious <hi>Name:</hi> moue thee to <hi>confeſse,</hi> and ſay to him in particular for this exchange; Bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> which hath not put backe my <hi>prayer</hi> from himſelfe, nor his <hi>mercy</hi> from me. His <hi>Name</hi> be extolled; his <hi>Name</hi> bee <hi>prayſed;</hi> his moſt <hi>glorious Name</hi> be bleſſed for <hi>euer,</hi> and <hi>euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:150664:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A ſhort Treatiſe vpon the thirtie one and thirtie two Verſes, of the one <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſeuenth</hi> PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The driſt.</note> ſetting forth the great <hi>praiſe</hi> of GOD, by this whole <hi>Pſalme;</hi> Firſt,
<note place="margin">The parts.</note> in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall propoſition of the ſame in the firſt <hi>Verſe,</hi> doth ſet it alſo forth. Secondly, by certaine particular inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or preſidents of his moſt <hi>praiſe</hi>-worthy adminiſtration towards ſundry moſt calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and <hi>diſtreſsed,</hi> perſons:
<note place="margin">The ending of each Narration.</note> ending the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of each of theſe, with one and the ſame ſpeciall <hi>Exhortation.</hi> As alſo his gracious <hi>dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> towards miſerable wanderers, <hi>harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse,</hi> and ſuccourleſſe in ſtrange Countries. His moſt fauourable regard of <hi>wofull</hi> inthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>captiues</hi> vnder the yrons of cruell Tyrants. His wondrous mercy extended to ſuch as were <hi>ſore</hi> broken with violent <hi>ſickneſſe;</hi> and his admirall reliefe to ſuch Sea-faring men, as were in ſuch deſperate ieopardie, as no <hi>way</hi> but lamentable periſhing, without his preſent powerfull helpe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150664:43"/>
               <hi>O that men would praiſe the Lord for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 31.</note> and for his wonderfull workes to the children of men!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 32.</note> Let them exalt him alſo in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the people and praiſe him in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or thus rather: <hi>Let them Confeſſe, Magnifie, Praiſe,</hi> To, Or <hi>before</hi> IEHOVA, <hi>his benignitie, and his maruellous workes to, or, before the ſonnes of men: And let them exalt him in the congregation of the people: and in the aſsembly of Elders let them praiſe him.</hi>]
<note place="margin">What theſe verſes are.</note> Which two Verſes are an ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied exhortation to excellent Thankeſgiuing, teaching indeed (and without being more curious then the <hi>Text</hi> doth intend) thus much vnto vs:
<note place="margin">What they teach.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> That it is the duty of euery one releaſed out of miſery, and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry partaker of <hi>Gods</hi> benignitie; both priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publikely to <hi>praiſe</hi> his <hi>goodneſse,</hi> his <hi>workes,</hi> and <hi>himſelfe</hi> moſt worthily.</p>
            <p>It is the dutie of the firſt ſort,
<note place="margin">Proofe of the firſt and ſecond point.</note> by expreſſe precept in ſix <hi>Verſes</hi> of this <hi>Pſalme:</hi> it is alſo the dutie of the ſecond ſort, as by the direct command of the 11. and 12. <hi>Verſes</hi> of the 148. <hi>Pſalme:</hi> ſo by implication in the ſaid <hi>Verſes</hi> of this ſaid <hi>Pſalme;</hi> as the learned <hi>Tranſlatours</hi> of the New <hi>Tranſlation</hi> doe witneſſe, in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150664:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>indefinitely, <hi>O that men would praiſe the Lord!</hi> Now it is their duty, to what? Why,
<note place="margin">Of the third</note> both priuately: for, to, or <hi>with,</hi> or <hi>before Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> as it vſed to bee rendred, intimateth that ſecret <hi>deuotion,</hi> which in <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Chriſt</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth, and commandeth to his Diſciples. Alſo <hi>publikely:</hi> for, to, or <hi>before the ſonnes of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of the fourth.</note> meaneth that open <hi>deuotion</hi> which all are to ioyne together, called next by way of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> The praiſing of <hi>God</hi> in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the <hi>aſsembly.</hi> This dutie here,
<note place="margin">Of the fifth.</note> is to <hi>praiſe,</hi> Firſt, Gods goodneſſe, <hi>Magnifie to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa his benignity.</hi> Secondly, His noble works, <hi>and his maruellous workes.</hi> Thirdly, Himſelfe, <hi>exalt him, praiſe him:</hi> and how? Moſt worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For all theſe circumſtances,
<note place="margin">Of the ſixth.</note> 
               <hi>praiſe his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous or wonderfull workes, and exalt him;</hi> and that before himſelfe, and in the congregation of the people, and in the aſſembly of <hi>Elders;</hi> doe confirme this worthieſt manner of doing this dutie. Now to come to the application of this Doctrine:</p>
            <p>O,
<note place="margin">Application to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note> we that haue been releaſed by the Lords admirable mercy, out of any miſery, grieuous corporall miſery, or which is worſer, grieuous <hi>ſpirituall</hi> miſery;
<note place="margin">The things reprooued.</note> O let vs thinke of our forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, of our neglect of this dutie <hi>priuately,</hi> or <hi>publikely,</hi> and worthily to praiſe our gracious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150664:44"/>
               <hi>God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How to thinke of theſe.</note> let vs euen ſeriouſly, and heauily thinke hereon to be aſhamed of our vnthankfull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulnes, and negligence, &amp; to repent therof. To further this,
<note place="margin">How to ſearch theſe conſider Gods deſire.</note> ô let vs <hi>ſearch</hi> out and meaſure the grieuouſnes of this forgetting, and of this neglect: to this purpoſe conſider, Firſt, How it croſſeth <hi>Gods</hi> owne deſire; being releaſed, eaſed, deliuered, redeemed, healed, he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that we come and <hi>praiſe</hi> him; but we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it,
<note place="margin">The godlies vſe.</note> we neglect it, albeit he deſire it. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſecondly, how contrary we are herein to the examples of the ancient <hi>godly</hi> ones; ô where do we find in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> any of the true holy ones defamed with this forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">Idolaters practice.</note> and with this neglect? Conſider, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how, euen groſſe <hi>Idolaters</hi> may riſe vp to <hi>condemne</hi> vs; for which of them forget, or neglect to praiſe their abominable <hi>Idols,</hi> when they receiue any victory, or be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of any miſery?</p>
            <p>Conſider,
<note place="margin">Our taking on.</note> fourthly, how our own <hi>carriage</hi> in calamitie ſerueth to <hi>condemne</hi> theſe ſinnes. For when griefs are vpon vs we, pray, we cry, wee ſhead <hi>teares,</hi> we make <hi>vowes</hi> to God to moue him to <hi>helpe</hi> vs; and yet being helped, this dutie is forgotten, this dutie is neglected. Conſider,
<note place="margin">Our caſe.</note> fifthly, what a <hi>caſe</hi> wee were in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee were releaſed; what a farre more
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150664:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>grieuous <hi>eaſe</hi> we had beene in, if wee had not beene deliuered,
<note place="margin">Our vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe.</note> and how vnworthy wee are that the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould releeue vs at all. O let vs conſider all theſe, and then finding in our ſelues, that for all the ſame, yet we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, yet wee haue neglected this dutie of <hi>praiſe:</hi> let vs then confeſſe, and cry out: O,
<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> we haue <hi>ſinned,</hi> wee haue done <hi>wickedly: God</hi> hath remembred vs, and wee haue forgotten him; he hath been liberall to vs, and we haue beene vnthankfull to him: ô, we haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that our miſery ſhould haue been doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; ô, we are <hi>aſhamed;</hi> ô forgiue vs, <hi>Lord,</hi> ô, forgiue vs.</p>
            <p>And ô wee,
<note place="margin">Application to the latter things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued.</note> that are otherwiſe partakers of the louing kindneſſe of the <hi>Lord,</hi> let vs alſo thinke of our negligence, vnmindfulneſſe, and backewardneſſe to this dutie to repent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and to be aſhamed of the ſame: conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to that end; Firſt,
<note place="margin">to aggrauate theſe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods mind. The godlies vſe.</note> that it is againſt <hi>Gods</hi> mind that wee are ſo: for hee would haue vs thankfull for all his <hi>benefits</hi> we doe inioy. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is againſt the vſe of his right <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants:</hi> for they praiſe him, and as it is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.10. they <hi>bleſse</hi> him for all his goodnes.
<note place="margin">The vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſſe.</note> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is againſt all reaſon, that we being crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his <hi>benignitie,</hi> ſhould neglect this dutie: for wee deſerue none of it. Fourthly,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150664:45"/>many arguments make greatly againſt vs for our ingratitude.
<note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</note> Oh, what a thing is it, when <hi>happineſſe,</hi> when our owne gladneſſe, when others commending our <hi>estate,</hi> cannot awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs out of our neglect?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Happineſse;</hi> for as it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.15. The people are <hi>happie</hi> that haue ſuch bountie.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Gladneſse;</hi> for as it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. <hi>God</hi> by his goodneſſe, as wee find alſo in our experience, doth fil our very <hi>hearts</hi> with gladneſſe.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Others commendation; for as it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.2. They that <hi>behold Gods</hi> manifold <hi>bleſsings</hi> vpon vs, doe ſay that hee hath done <hi>great</hi> things for vs.
<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> Oh, if we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe forget and neglect this <hi>dutie;</hi> let vs <hi>confeſſe;</hi> let vs <hi>repent;</hi> let vs be aſhamed, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: let vs alſo <hi>iudge</hi> our ſelues worthy to haue it ſaid of vs, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. Do you ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the <hi>Lord,</hi> ô you fooliſh people, and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe?</hi> worthy that the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould conteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. ſaying, <hi>Heare</hi> ô <hi>Heauens,</hi> and giue eare, ô <hi>Earth:</hi> I haue nouriſhed, and brought vp children, and they haue rebelled againſt me. Worthy that he ſhould take all our abundance, our riches, our comforts, our peace, our honours from vs: ſhould powre <hi>contempt</hi> vpon vs, ſhould turne our <hi>riuers</hi> into drie <hi>land;</hi> our water-ſprings into a wildernes, our fruitfull <hi>land</hi> into barrennes, &amp; humble vs
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150664:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnder ſore oppreſſion, affliction, and ſorrow.</p>
            <p>And, let both ſorts of vs now at the <hi>length,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admonition to both.</note> ſettle our <hi>hearts</hi> to the ſincere practice of this dutie of <hi>priuate, publike,</hi> and worthy praiſe to <hi>God,</hi> euen to bring forth fruit worthy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this <hi>point.</hi> O,
<note place="margin">A deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt.</note> wee that haue felt the fainting of our <hi>ſoules;</hi> that haue beene in ſore <hi>trouble;</hi> that haue (as it were) ſit in <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and the ſhadow of <hi>death;</hi> that haue beene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen bound vp in <hi>affliction;</hi> that haue had our <hi>hearts</hi> brought downe with heauineſſe; that haue had our <hi>life</hi> next ſtep to the <hi>gates</hi> of <hi>death;</hi> that haue had our ſpirits melted away with <hi>perplexitie;</hi> that haue beene compaſſed about with moſt <hi>wofull</hi> miſeries, and that haue ſeene how when we <hi>cryed</hi> vnto the Lord, hee brought vs out of our darkeneſſe; he deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs out of all our diſtreſſes; he ſatisfied our longing ſoules; he healed vs. Let vs, ô let vs now practiſe cheerefully and readily this holy dutie.</p>
            <p>To incite vs thereunto, let vs conſider: Firſt,
<note place="margin">To moue the firſt to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, conſider Gods readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> 
               <hi>Gods</hi> exceeding readineſſe to <hi>heare</hi> vs, and his preſentneſſe to deliuer vs; yea, though our <hi>afflictions</hi> came on vs, becauſe wee had rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt his Word, becauſe we had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, becauſe of our <hi>iniquities.</hi> Secondly,
<note place="margin">Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerablenes.</note> 
               <hi>Gods</hi> fulfilling of our very wiſhes, &amp; bringing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150664:46"/>vs to the very <hi>ſtate</hi> we deſired. Thirdly, the <hi>due</hi> time,
<note place="margin">Time, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, meanes.</note> the <hi>ſweet</hi> manner, the gracious <hi>meanes</hi> of his deliuerance of vs. Fourthly, the paſſing <hi>comfort</hi> we found,
<note place="margin">The ſequent comfort.</note> after hee had deliuered vs, filling, as it is, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 126.2. our mouth with <hi>laughter,</hi> and our <hi>tongue</hi> with ſinging.</p>
            <p>And,
<note place="margin">A deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſecond.</note> ô wee that haue not yet come where any ſorrow, woe, bitterneſſe, <hi>worme-wood</hi> hath beene put into our <hi>cup:</hi> but we only haue lyen downe in greene <hi>paſtures,</hi> and walked along beſide the ſtill waters, and our <hi>table</hi> hath been alway <hi>richly</hi> furniſhed, our <hi>head</hi> anointed with <hi>oyle,</hi> our <hi>cup</hi> running ouer, <hi>goodneſſe</hi> and mercy following vs all the dayes of our life. O let vs, let vs alſo, if not much rather apply with haſte, and haſte with godly <hi>zeale,</hi> vnto this <hi>duty,</hi> vrging our mindes thereto with theſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Conſidering;
<note place="margin">To moue the ſecond, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider receit.</note> Firſt, that all our <hi>comforts,</hi> are things meerely receiued, as 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. What haſt thou, that thou didſt not <hi>receiue?</hi> Secondly,
<note place="margin">Whence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</note> that they bee all receiued from <hi>Gods</hi> good <hi>pleaſure,</hi> as of corporall things it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.16. Thou openeſt thine <hi>hand,</hi> and <hi>filleſt</hi> euery liuing thing of thy owne <hi>good</hi> will: and of <hi>ſpirituall</hi> things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>God</hi> worketh the will and the deed, of his owne good <hi>pleaſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vndeſert.</note> Thirdly, that all the <hi>bountie</hi> we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150664:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>inioy, is contrary to our <hi>deſert:</hi> for as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> 9.7. To vs belongeth <hi>confuſion,</hi> or ſhame of <hi>face.</hi> Fourthly, that our proſperitie,
<note place="margin">All as we would haue them.</note> our <hi>choyſe,</hi> our <hi>matches,</hi> our <hi>bargaines,</hi> our <hi>dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> our <hi>friends,</hi> our <hi>alliance,</hi> our <hi>food,</hi> our <hi>rayment,</hi> our <hi>peace,</hi> our <hi>meanes,</hi> our <hi>aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> our <hi>times,</hi> our <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> our <hi>affaires,</hi> yea and our <hi>Sabbaths</hi> are euen as we would haue them; as if that were verified to vs, which is ſaid of the true <hi>fearers</hi> of <hi>God, Pſal.</hi> 145.19. Hee fulfilleth the deſire of them that feare him. O let vs conſider theſe things;</p>
            <p>And let theſe perſwade vs to the <hi>dutie</hi> here required of both kinds of vs:
<note place="margin">Effect of the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</note> for ſurely theſe rightly <hi>weighed,</hi> cannot but make vs ſay, O come, and wee ſhall <hi>tell</hi> you what <hi>God</hi> hath done for our <hi>ſoules:</hi> O magnifie the <hi>Lord</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with vs: O, what ſhall wee render vnto the <hi>Lord</hi> for all his <hi>benefits?</hi> O, we will <hi>pay</hi> our <hi>vowes,</hi> which our <hi>lips</hi> haue vttered, and which our <hi>mouthes</hi> haue ſpoken in our <hi>affliction:</hi> O, wee will doe our <hi>dutie</hi> of ſolemne <hi>praiſe</hi> vnto him priuately, <hi>publikely,</hi> and worthily. O that men would ſo <hi>praiſe</hi> the <hi>Lord;</hi> O that <hi>high</hi> and <hi>low</hi> would ſo praiſe the <hi>Lord;</hi> O that euery one would, as they are moſt <hi>bounden,</hi> ſo praiſe the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praiſe</hi> him ſo, priuately:
<note place="margin">How praiſe priuately.</note> priuately with the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150664:47"/>
               <hi>family,</hi> as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> with his <hi>family;</hi> more <hi>priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> with ſome of the <hi>family,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> with <hi>Iſaac;</hi> moſt priuately alone, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> moſt often: and in <hi>priuate</hi> ſay vnto him,
<note place="margin">Patterne of this priuate.</note> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.1, 2. It is a <hi>good</hi> thing to giue all <hi>thanks</hi> vnto thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> euen to ſing prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnto thy <hi>Name,</hi> O moſt <hi>High:</hi> yea, to ſhew forth thy louing kindneſſe euery <hi>morning,</hi> and thy <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> euery night: as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.16, 17. Oh <hi>Lord,</hi> verily I am thy <hi>ſeruant,</hi> I am thy <hi>ſeruant,</hi> and the ſonne of thine <hi>handmaid;</hi> thou haſt looſed my <hi>bonds,</hi> I will <hi>offer</hi> vnto thee the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> of <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> and will call on thy <hi>Name, O Lord.</hi> And <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.21, 28. I will <hi>praiſe</hi> thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> for thou haſt <hi>heard</hi> mee, and art become my <hi>ſaluation:</hi> thou art my <hi>God,</hi> and I will <hi>praiſe</hi> thee: thou art my <hi>God,</hi> and I will <hi>exalt</hi> thee: and as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.33, 34. I will <hi>ſing</hi> vnto thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> as long as I <hi>liue:</hi> I will ſing <hi>praiſe</hi> to thee my <hi>God,</hi> while I haue any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; my <hi>meditation</hi> of thee ſhall bee <hi>ſweet:</hi> I will be <hi>glad</hi> in thee. O, after this <hi>bleſsed</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, let euery one <hi>praiſe God</hi> priuately.</p>
            <p>Euery one <hi>praiſe</hi> him alſo <hi>publikely:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How praiſe publikely in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the people.</note> both in ordinary on euery <hi>Sabbath;</hi> with addition of more <hi>thankes,</hi> and more <hi>zeale</hi> in thanking, on the <hi>Sabbaths</hi> of <hi>celebrating</hi> the <hi>holy Supper</hi> of the <hi>Lord:</hi> alſo, in extraordinary, on the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150664:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>dayes</hi> of ſolemne <hi>publike</hi> thankeſgiuing, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 12.27, 43. and <hi>Eſter</hi> 9.17. and let euery one <hi>profeſse</hi> concerning this <hi>publike,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.3.
<note place="margin">Patterns of this.</note> O <hi>magnifie</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> with mee, and let vs <hi>exalt</hi> his <hi>Name</hi> together: and as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 108.3. I will praiſe thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>people,</hi> and will ſing <hi>praiſes</hi> vnto thee among the Nations: and as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.1. I will praiſe the <hi>Lord</hi> with my whole <hi>heart</hi> in the <hi>aſſembly</hi> of the vpright, and in the <hi>congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation:</hi> and as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 109.30. I will greatly <hi>praiſe</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> with my mouth; yea, I will <hi>praiſe</hi> him among the <hi>multitude:</hi> and as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.18, 19. I will <hi>pay</hi> my <hi>vowes</hi> vnto the <hi>Lord</hi> now, in the preſence of all his <hi>people,</hi> in the Courts of the <hi>Lords</hi> Houſe, in the <hi>midſt</hi> of thee, ô <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O let euery one,
<note place="margin">How in the aſſembly of the Elders.</note> thus <hi>praiſe</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely in the congregation of the <hi>people:</hi> and not onely ſo, but alſo in the <hi>aſsembly</hi> of the Elders: if at any time (as they ought) the Princes and great ones doe aſſemble, vpon ſpeciall <hi>occaſion</hi> together, to giue <hi>glory</hi> vnto the Lord: euen <hi>glory</hi> vnto his <hi>Name,</hi> and to <hi>worſhip</hi> him in the <hi>beautie</hi> of Holineſſe: as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.1, 2. they are commanded; and as, becauſe God hath done greater honour to them, then to meaner <hi>people,</hi> they are more
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150664:48"/>
               <hi>bounden:</hi> O let euery one, who hath any cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be amongſt them, as a <hi>teacher,</hi> or as an hearer, or as otherwiſe conuented, praiſe the Lord euen before them alſo, and ſay concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this,
<note place="margin">Patternes of this.</note> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.46. <hi>O Lord,</hi> I will ſpeake of thy <hi>teſtimonies</hi> euen before Kings, and will not bee <hi>aſhamed:</hi> and as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.1. I will <hi>praiſe</hi> thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> with my whole <hi>heart:</hi> yea, before the <hi>gods,</hi> or great <hi>Potentates</hi> will I ſing <hi>praiſe</hi> vnto thee. O, thus let vs praiſe the <hi>Lord</hi> priuately in his owne preſence, publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the congregation of the <hi>people;</hi> boldly, in the <hi>aſſembly</hi> of the Elders.</p>
            <p>Let none of vs be like the wicked,
<note place="margin">Who are contrary to theſe.</note> whoſe ſecret <hi>cloſets</hi> are for ſecret <hi>ſinnes;</hi> but not for ſecret <hi>duties</hi> of godlineſſe: whoſe priuate houſes are for priuate ſports, paſtimes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, pleaſures: but not for priuate prayers, and praiſes to <hi>God.</hi> Neither let vs be like the <hi>popiſh</hi> Recuſant, or the ſelfe-weening <hi>Separatiſt;</hi> who diſdaine the congregation of the people, and haue their owne will-worſhips for corners, but no praiſe for the <hi>Lord</hi> in publike <hi>Temples.</hi> Neither let vs be like the timorous and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who dare not profeſſe <hi>God</hi> before the <hi>gods,</hi> nor praiſe the <hi>Lord</hi> before <hi>lords;</hi> but trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly lay their <hi>hand</hi> vpon their <hi>lips,</hi> when their <hi>mouth</hi> ſhould be open to ſhew forth his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150664:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>praiſe. Let theſe euils be farre from vs, and let vs <hi>laud</hi> the Lord our God with <hi>conſcience</hi> in priuate, with cheerefulneſſe in publike, and with <hi>courage</hi> before the Elders.</p>
            <p>Thus praiſe his <hi>benignitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The praiſe of Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity: that it is Ancient,</note> thus praiſe his wonderfull <hi>workes,</hi> and thus praiſe himſelfe. O praiſe his benignity, by <hi>commending,</hi> Firſt, the ancientneſſe thereof, for as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.6. His ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies, and his louing <hi>kindneſſes</hi> haue beene euer of old. Secondly,
<note place="margin">Great,</note> the <hi>greatneſse</hi> thereof: for as <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.17, 25. his is great kindneſſe, and great <hi>goodneſse.</hi> Thirdly, the <hi>richneſſe</hi> thereof: for as <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.
<note place="margin">Rich, Admirable,</note> there is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his goodneſſe. Fourthly, the <hi>admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes</hi> thereof: for, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19. O how mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous is the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> that hee hath laid vp for them that <hi>feare</hi> him; yea, which hee hath already wrought for them that truſt in him, before the ſonnes of men? Fifthly,
<note place="margin">Excellent,</note> the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie thereof: for, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.7. How excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is his louing kindneſſe! Sixthly,
<note place="margin">Immeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</note> the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurableneſſe</hi> thereof: for, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18. O the <hi>breadth,</hi> and <hi>length,</hi> the <hi>depth,</hi> and <hi>height</hi> of his <hi>mercy!</hi> Seuenthly,
<note place="margin">Cauſe of all goods.</note> the <hi>endleſneſſe</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. It indureth for euer, and euer. Eighthly, the <hi>effects</hi> thereof, as <hi>Titus</hi> 3.4, 5. Out of it comes <hi>mercie</hi> to ſaue vs: as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 63.3, 5. comes that to vs, which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150664:49"/>then life, and which ſatisfieth our <hi>ſoules</hi> as with <hi>marrow</hi> and <hi>fatnes:</hi> as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 65.12. It is that which the <hi>yeere</hi> is <hi>crowned</hi> with ſuch <hi>bleſsings,</hi> ſuch <hi>fatnes,</hi> ſuch abundance, ſuch flouriſhing <hi>flockes,</hi> ſuch goodly <hi>corne,</hi> as cauſeth all <hi>people</hi> to ſing, &amp; ſhowt for <hi>ioy:</hi> ſaying, Therfore, how <hi>ancient</hi> how <hi>great?</hi> how <hi>rich?</hi> how <hi>admirable?</hi> how <hi>excellent?</hi> how <hi>immeaſurable?</hi> how end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe? how fruitful is the <hi>benignity</hi> of the <hi>Lord? praiſe</hi> it before him; <hi>praiſe</hi> it before the ſons of men; <hi>praiſe</hi> it before the congregation of the <hi>people; praiſe</hi> it before the <hi>aſsembly</hi> of the <hi>elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo praiſe his wonderfull <hi>workes</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs,
<note place="margin">To praiſe his wonderfull workes, by looking back two wayes:</note> or others in our <hi>miſeries.</hi> Firſt, <hi>praiſe</hi> them by looking backe to his goodneſſe and power, ſhewed, in doing that hee did for vs, when he <hi>redeemed</hi> vs, when he <hi>deliuered</hi> vs, when he <hi>healed vs,</hi> when he <hi>brought</hi> vs to that we deſired: by looking <hi>backe</hi> alſo to his <hi>power</hi> and goodnes ſhewed in <hi>preſeruing</hi> vs, in <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting</hi> vs, in <hi>ſtaying</hi> vs from <hi>periſhing,</hi> from being beneath, from finall <hi>perdition</hi> in our moſt <hi>forlorne</hi> caſe, vntill he did deliuer vs. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<note place="margin">By acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement,</note> 
               <hi>praiſe</hi> them by acknowledgement of his <hi>might,</hi> &amp; his <hi>will</hi> to be alone, and ſingular herein: ſaying, <hi>O Lord,</hi> who can, or who could, who will, or would haue done ſuch <hi>workes</hi> for vs, as thou haſt done? None would, none
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150664:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>could,</hi> but thou onely; thou only, to whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is hid, nothing <hi>hard,</hi> nothing <hi>impoſsible;</hi> who neuer <hi>fainteſt,</hi> art neuer <hi>weary,</hi> and of whoſe <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> there is no ſearching. Thirdly, <hi>praiſe</hi> them,
<note place="margin">By admiring</note> by admiring his doing of them vnto vs: ſaying, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.4. O what is <hi>man,</hi> that thou art <hi>mindfull</hi> of him? What is the <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>mortall</hi> man, that thou <hi>viſiteſt</hi> him? and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.3. <hi>Lord,</hi> what is <hi>man,</hi> that thou takeſt knowledge of him? or the <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> that thou makeſt <hi>account</hi> of him?</p>
            <p>And helpe this <hi>admiration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Helps to this admiration, by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what we are.</note> by thinking how we are, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. all of vs by <hi>nature</hi> the children of <hi>wrath:</hi> and <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3, 5. Of our owne wee are naught but <hi>ſinfull</hi> fleſh, euery imagination of the thoughts of our heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely euill <hi>continually:</hi> and <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.27. We are but <hi>duſt</hi> and <hi>aſhes:</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.8. We are <hi>tranſgreſſours</hi> from the <hi>wombe:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.4. We are but <hi>vanitie,</hi> and our <hi>dayes</hi> as a <hi>ſhadow</hi> that <hi>paſſeth</hi> away: and <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. The <hi>holieſt</hi> are but miſerable and wretched. O <hi>marke</hi> theſe <hi>well,</hi> &amp; wonder at Gods workes of grace, of <hi>mercy,</hi> and of <hi>louing</hi> kindneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: <hi>praiſe</hi> them before him, <hi>praiſe</hi> them to the ſonnes of men: ſaying as heere,
<note place="margin">Patternes of this prayſe.</note> Surely theſe workes of the <hi>Lord</hi> are wonderfull workes: and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.2, 3, 4. They are great,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150664:50"/>they are honourable, they are glorious <hi>works,</hi> oh he hath ſo done, and ſo wrought the ſame, as he hath <hi>made</hi> them to be <hi>remembred</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Say, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.4. Verily theſe <hi>works</hi> are the praiſes of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Say, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 92.4, 5. Thou, <hi>Lord,</hi> haſt made me <hi>glad</hi> through thy workes: I will <hi>triumph</hi> in the workes of thine <hi>hands. O Lord,</hi> how great is thy workes, and thy thoughts are very deepe?</p>
            <p>Oh,
<note place="margin">Sins againſt Gods bonig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: Not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, Preſuming, Deſpiſing. Sins againſt his workes: Not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,</note> be it farre from vs to be guiltie of that complained of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.7. Not to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the multitude of his <hi>mercies:</hi> or that in <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. to preſume to <hi>ſinne,</hi> through ſawcie <hi>confidence</hi> in his <hi>mercy:</hi> or that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. To deſpiſe the riches of his goodneſſe: or that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.6. To be ſo bruitiſh, as not to acknowledge his <hi>workes,</hi> and ſo fooliſh, as not to diſcerne the ſame: or that in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 28.5. Not to regard his <hi>workes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. Sins againſt himſelfe:</note> or that in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 95.9. To prouoke and <hi>tempt</hi> him, though wee haue ſeene his <hi>glorious workes:</hi> or that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4, 5, 13.
<note place="margin">Not to ſeek, Not to thinke,</note> To be ſo proud, as not to ſeek God, as not to haue him in our thoughts, as to thinke his <hi>wayes</hi> alway grieuous vnto vs,
<note place="margin">To contemn.</note> as euen to <hi>contemne</hi> him. O farre be theſe from vs: and as it is ſaid, <hi>Iob</hi> 21.16. Farre bee the <hi>counſell</hi> of all ſuch from vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To praiſe. himſelfe.</note> whom, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.1. <hi>praiſe</hi> waiteth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150664:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>on in <hi>Sion:</hi> himſelfe, who is, as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 18.3. moſt worthy to be <hi>praiſed:</hi> himſelfe, who <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.3. inhabiteth the praiſes of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> himſelfe, whoſe <hi>praiſes, Pſal.</hi> 78.4. the <hi>godly</hi> doe ſhew to their <hi>poſteritie:</hi> himſelfe, to whom, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 147.1. it is good, and pleaſant, and comely to ſing praiſes: himſelfe, who, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 145.3. is great, and greatly to bee <hi>praiſed:</hi> himſelfe, who, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.21. is our God, and our <hi>praiſe,</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Him, euen him let vs <hi>praiſe</hi> worthily,
<note place="margin">To prayſe him worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is, To exalt him.</note> which in one word, is to exalt him: let vs ſo <hi>praiſe</hi> him, as we <hi>exalt</hi> him: not our <hi>ſelues,</hi> but our God: for as <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.12. Whoſoeuer <hi>exalteth</hi> himſelfe, he ſhall be <hi>abaſed:</hi> not <hi>Idols,</hi> but the <hi>Lord,</hi> for as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 97.7. Confounded be all they that ſerue and reioyce in, and ſo exalt <hi>Idols.</hi> No, no, but the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> let vs exalt him alone: let vs exhort others to exalt him,
<note place="margin">Exhorting others.</note> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.5. Exalt yee the Lord our God: let vs in our <hi>ſelues</hi> exalt him, ſaying, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.1.
<note place="margin">Doing it our ſelues.</note> O <hi>Lord,</hi> thou art my <hi>God,</hi> I will exalt thee, and praiſe thy <hi>Name;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Patternes.</note> for thou haſt done wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things. Let the <hi>progeny</hi> of the <hi>godly</hi> exalt him, ſaying, <hi>Exodus</hi> 15.2. The <hi>Lord</hi> is my ſtrength, and <hi>ſong,</hi> he is become my <hi>ſaluation,</hi> he is my <hi>God,</hi> and he is my fathers <hi>God:</hi> I will prepare him an <hi>habitation,</hi> and I will exalt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150664:51"/>him: thus <hi>praiſe</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> owne ſelfe, by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting</hi> him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exalt</hi> him;
<note place="margin">Exalt him: ſet all vnder him, in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</note> ſet all vnder him in the <hi>congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: cry,</hi> Downe with <hi>Idols,</hi> downe with <hi>Images,</hi> down with <hi>mens</hi> deuices, downe with <hi>Inuocation</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> downe with <hi>worſhipping</hi> of <hi>Angels;</hi> and intertaine and exalt in the congregation of his <hi>people,</hi> none but his owne <hi>ordinances,</hi> his owne <hi>Word,</hi> his owne <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> his owne <hi>Name,</hi> his owne <hi>ſelfe.</hi> Exalt him:
<note place="margin">In the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Elders,</note> ſet all vnder him in the <hi>aſsembly</hi> of Elders: Bid them, as <hi>Reu.</hi> 4.11, 10. fall downe before him, <hi>worſhip</hi> him, and caſt downe their <hi>crownes</hi> at his <hi>feet.</hi> Bid them, <hi>ſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. be <hi>wiſe,</hi> and bee <hi>inſtructed</hi> to <hi>ſerue</hi> him with <hi>fear,</hi> &amp; to reioyce before him with trembling. Bid them, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.1, 2. giue to him <hi>glory,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and giue to him the <hi>glory</hi> due to his <hi>Name.
<note place="margin">In the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</note> Exalt</hi> him, ſet all vnder him in the Family: <hi>Wiues, children, ſeruants,</hi> in your duties feare the <hi>Lord,</hi> looke vp vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> do all your <hi>ſeruice</hi> of ſubiection, and <hi>obedience,</hi> as vnto the <hi>Lord. Husbands, fathers, masters, rule,</hi> as vnder the <hi>Lord,</hi> exalt him as your <hi>Maſter</hi> which is in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exalt</hi> him,
<note place="margin">Set him aboue all.</note> ſet him aboue all, ſay, as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 136.2, 3. Thou art <hi>God</hi> of <hi>gods,</hi> thou art <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>lords:</hi> ſay, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.21, 22. Thou, <hi>O Lord,</hi> art
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150664:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>farre aboue all <hi>principalitie,</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>might,</hi> and <hi>dominion,</hi> and euery <hi>Name</hi> that is <hi>named,</hi> not onely in this <hi>world,</hi> but in that alſo which is to <hi>come:</hi> all things are vnder thy <hi>feet:</hi> ſay, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.19. Thou art the moſt High <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>poſſeſſour</hi> of Heauen and Earth. Thus <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt</hi> him:
<note place="margin">Set moſt by him.</note> exalt him alſo in ſetting more by him then all, ſaying, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.25. Whom haue I in <hi>heauen</hi> but thee? and there is none in <hi>earth</hi> that I deſire beſides thee. <hi>Exalt</hi> him, in ſetting <hi>praiſes</hi> on him more then on all,
<note place="margin">Set moſt praiſes on him,</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O Lord,</hi> I more delight in thee, then in <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or <hi>mother,</hi> or <hi>wife,</hi> or <hi>children,</hi> or <hi>friends,</hi> or <hi>goods,</hi> or <hi>pleaſures,</hi> or <hi>lands;</hi> yea, as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 63.3. Thy louing <hi>kindneſſe</hi> is better to me then <hi>life</hi> it ſelfe. Thou art my <hi>portion,</hi> my <hi>glory,</hi> and <hi>ſong. Exalt</hi> him,
<note place="margin">Set apart chiefe place for him,</note> in ſetting apart a chiefe <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation</hi> for him to dwell in, euen thy <hi>ſoule</hi> all trimmed, as, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2. A <hi>lowly,</hi> a <hi>poore,</hi> a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſpirit,</hi> trembling at his <hi>Word.
<note place="margin">Prefer place and meanes of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, Be at coſt to ſerue him,</note> Exalt</hi> him, in preferring a <hi>place,</hi> and meanes for his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,</hi> before all thine owne <hi>comforts,</hi> as <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 132. <hi>Exalt</hi> him, in being at coſt to <hi>ſerue</hi> him, as the ſame royall <hi>perſon,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Exalt</hi> him, in giuing him the beſt <hi>ſeruice</hi> of all,
<note place="margin">Giue him beſt ſeruice,</note> that is, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. thy <hi>body,</hi> and thy whole ſelfe a liuing <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> holy,
<note place="margin">Giue him beſt diſh.</note> and acceptable vnto him. <hi>Exalt</hi> him, in giuing him the beſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150664:52"/>
               <hi>diſh,</hi> euen as <hi>Prou.</hi> 23.26. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6. thy very heart abounding with <hi>ſincerity,</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> in all the inward <hi>parts</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>O, that men would thus <hi>praiſe</hi> the <hi>Lord priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> publikely, and worthily: O, that we had our minds heated, &amp; inflamed by al this that hath bin ſaid, with holy <hi>zeale,</hi> to tye our ſelues thus to <hi>confeſſe</hi> before the Lord his louing kindnes and his wonderfull <hi>workes</hi> before the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men; thus to exalt him in the congregation, and euery where; thus to praiſe him alſo in the Aſſembly of the <hi>Elders.</hi> But, who is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for this <hi>Angelicall duty?</hi>
               <note place="margin">How to come to the grace to prayſe God thus.</note> Of our ſelues we haue not a thought towards it: God is the <hi>owner,</hi> and God is the <hi>giuer</hi> of it; therefore that we may performe it to him, we muſt firſt <hi>craue</hi> it at him, ſaying with the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.15. O Lord, open thou my <hi>lips,</hi> and my <hi>mouth</hi> ſhall ſhew <hi>forth</hi> thy <hi>praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt wee deceiue our ſelues,
<note place="margin">Proofes of ſuch as doe prayſe God.</note> thinking we be of the number of thoſe that <hi>praiſe</hi> God rightly, when indeed we be not, we muſt note the proofes of ſuch as doe <hi>praiſe</hi> him, his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie,</hi> and his <hi>workes</hi> ſoundly, and examine our ſelues of them. Firſt, If we haue this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>grace</hi> to <hi>praiſe</hi> him; then wee find in our ſelues,
<note place="margin">Affecting of God.</note> that we ſo <hi>affect</hi> the Lord, as we ſeeke, we <hi>thirſt,</hi> we long greatly after him, and after
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150664:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>exerciſes</hi> of his <hi>worſhip:</hi> for this, in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 63. is ſhewed to be in him whoſe <hi>mouth praiſeth</hi> the Lord with ioyfull lips. Secondly, If wee haue this <hi>grace</hi> to praiſe his benignitie,
<note place="margin">Leading to repentance by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity.</note> then we find in our ſelues that it leadeth vs vnto <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> as it is ſaid it ought to doe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. ſo as our loue is ſet vpon it, more then <hi>life,</hi> as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 63.3. and it moueth vs to <hi>walke</hi> truely, and godly in Gods ſight: for this in the ſaid Pſalme, and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. is ſpoken of him that compaſſeth Gods Altar with the <hi>voyce</hi> of Thankeſgiuing. Thirdly,
<note place="margin">His workes affect vs with loue, &amp;c.</note> If wee haue this <hi>grace</hi> of <hi>pratſing</hi> Gods wonderfull workes; then we find in our ſelues a louing of them, a taking pleaſure in them, a <hi>gladneſſe</hi> in them, a <hi>reioycing</hi> in them, a <hi>gracious</hi> acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, a holy ſhewing of them to our <hi>poſteritie,</hi> a deſire to come to <hi>praiſe</hi> God in the aſſembly for them: for theſe are ſaid, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. and 92. and 78. and 26. of ſuch as haue this <hi>grace</hi> of magnifying GODS <hi>workes.</hi> Fourthly, If wee haue the true Art of <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> God, we find in our ſelues,
<note place="margin">Ordering our life well.</note> that we order our life well: for in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. this is ioyned with the <hi>offering</hi> of praiſe vnto God. O, let vs looke to theſe <hi>proofes</hi> of our fitneſſe to this <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> if we haue them not: then, as in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.16. God calleth vs <hi>wicked,</hi> and challengeth vs of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150664:53"/>vile audaciouſnes for meddling with any <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> dutie: but if we haue them, then he ſaith, to incourage and to comfort vs, that wee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him.</p>
            <p>Which is the <hi>marke</hi> that in all things,
<note place="margin">Gods glory our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yme.</note> and eſpecially in Thankſgiuing we muſt ſhoot at: for his <hi>glory</hi> is the chiefe end of all. Being now come, and heereafter comming to the <hi>Sermons,</hi> and to the action of Thankſgiuing, let vs euer think of <hi>Gods glory;</hi> for he wil haue vs doe this <hi>dutie</hi> for his meere <hi>glory:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Difference of this duty from others.</note> all other <hi>duties</hi> of his <hi>ſeruice,</hi> are almoſt onely for our <hi>neceſsitie;</hi> but this all for his <hi>glory:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Pſalme</hi> 66.2. it is called a <hi>ſinging</hi> forth of the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>Name:</hi> and in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 29.2. a giuing of <hi>glory</hi> due to his <hi>Name.</hi> And wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily: becauſe if we be <hi>skilfull</hi> in it, wee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpeake ſuch <hi>great</hi> things of him, and of his <hi>properties,</hi> and of his <hi>workes,</hi> and of his <hi>Name,</hi> according to a ſpeciall parterne, in the 145. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and many others, as wee ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee a <hi>glorious</hi> God, and his <hi>Name,</hi> to bee a moſt <hi>glorious Name.</hi> O that men would ſo <hi>praiſe</hi> him in ſecret, in the family, in the congregation of the people, in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Elders,
<note place="margin">The lerme of this duty.</note> as they might thus ſhew his glory. And, ô, that this might not be at ſome ſeldome fits, but as <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 145.2. euery
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150664:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>day: and as <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 146.2. while wee doe liue, and while we haue any being.</p>
            <p>Note a ſpeciall <hi>rule</hi> how to continue this alway in our ſelues, and in our <hi>families:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rules to continue it in our ſelues.</note> in our ſelues to continue it, the <hi>rule</hi> is this, To haue his <hi>louing</hi> kindneſſe; his euerlaſting <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> his <hi>holy</hi> remembrance; his continuall <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits;</hi> and the <hi>promiſes</hi> of the better <hi>life</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in our <hi>thoughts,</hi> and (as it were) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our <hi>eyes,</hi> with a blameleſſe <hi>conuerſation,</hi> and a conſcience of thankeſgiuing. If wee obſerue this <hi>rule,</hi> wee ſhall neuer <hi>ceaſe</hi> to <hi>praiſe</hi> the Lord in our ſelues.
<note place="margin">Rules to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it in our families.</note> To bee the like in our <hi>families,</hi> the <hi>rule</hi> is not to entertaine, but to <hi>cut</hi> off from them euery <hi>popiſh, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, diſsolute,</hi> pick-thanke, <hi>ſlanderous,</hi> vaine, <hi>wicked,</hi> deceitfull, <hi>diſsembling,</hi> diſhoneſt, <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> vngodly, <hi>idle,</hi> irreligious <hi>perſon,</hi> and to maintaine (through all due reſpect yeelded to euery one in their place) <hi>peace, amitie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, vnitie;</hi> as there be no <hi>vnkindneſſes, iarres,</hi> contentions, <hi>breaches</hi> to make <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> of godly <hi>exerciſes.</hi> If this <hi>rule</hi> be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, then, as wee ſhall want no <hi>comfort, honour, commendation</hi> to our <hi>families:</hi> ſo in the ſame we ſhall <hi>bleſse</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God</hi> daily.</p>
            <p>Whereupon,
<note place="margin">The reward of this duty.</note> will follow the reward of this our thankfulneſſe to <hi>God;</hi> which is this,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150664:54"/>namely, That if it bee ſuch as we haue <hi>heard,</hi> and ſo attended with a well-diſpoſed <hi>way</hi> to preuent all occaſions of <hi>Gods diſhonour,</hi> and with a well-ordred life to promote the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>Name;</hi> then hee will let vs ſee, yea, cauſe vs to <hi>enioy</hi> his <hi>ſaluation,</hi> as it is <hi>promiſed, Pſalm.</hi> 50.23. not his deſtruction, as hee <hi>threatneth</hi> the vnthankefull wicked in the 22. Verſe,
<note place="margin">Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the thankefull.</note> but his ſaluation. So great <hi>account</hi> doth hee make of the <hi>right</hi> thankefull, as hee will not let them be ouer-<hi>wronged,</hi> taken <hi>away,</hi> or <hi>deſtroyed, ſuppreſsed, beaten</hi> downe, nor <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed:</hi> hee will not part with vs; hee will not be without vs: but that wee may ſtill <hi>honour</hi> him, <hi>praiſe</hi> him, and <hi>glorifie</hi> him; hee will keepe vs in <hi>ſafetie, preſerue</hi> vs in libertie, and <hi>maintaine</hi> vs in <hi>proſperitie,</hi> by the <hi>tower,</hi> the <hi>rocke,</hi> the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and the <hi>ſhield</hi> of his <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary ſaluation,</hi> and giue vs the <hi>comfort, peace, ioy, riches, glory,</hi> and in the end the <hi>conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the fulneſſe of his <hi>eternall</hi> ſaluation in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> for euer, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150664:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
